The Top Gear Car of the Year for 2000 is...
The Fiat Multipla.
And some of you still haven't forgiven us.
But twelve months on, will the Multipla
retain its controversial crown?
You, the car buying British public,
♪ "American Dream"
Jakatta
have a mind-boggling choice
of more than 2000 different new cars.
But don't worry, because
we're here to reveal the best,
in our Top Gear Awards special.
The problem is there is no
such thing as a bad car anymore.
Which means to win an award,
excellence is a necessity.
A car must be absolutely outstanding.
There are five different categories,
and there's something for everyone.
You know what they say.
Look after the pennies,
and the pounds will
look after themselves.
And if you're determined to get
the most medal for your money,
then make our Best Value award
part of your savings plan.
But, if your numbers do come up,
then, rest assured, we will show you
how to squander your lottery millions
with our Ultimate Dream Car.
We'll also be revealing the vehicle
no 21st century family should be without,
what the ideal mode of transport is
to make those endless shopping trips
and the school runs more bearable,
the Best Family Car.
And for those precious weekends
when you don't have to cart the kids around,
there's an award for the Best Driver's Car.
And finally, the
main announcement!
We will reveal the identity of the one car
that does more things better than any other,
Top Gear's Car of the Year 2001.
Time then, for the first award!
♪ "Fools Gold"
The Stone Roses
London, the Square Mile,
where the deals are done, and
personal wealth is measured in millions.
But the US economy is slowing,
and bonuses are set to be slashed.
So city boys, like everyone else,
will have to watch their spending.
But now, you've got an
important lesson to learn,
Getting value for money doesn't
necessarily mean buying cheap,
especially when it comes to cars.
In 2000, price cuts came from all quarters,
and with most manufacturers
having upped their specs,
more and more cars find themselves
eligible for the Best Value award.
Bargains last year came
in all shapes and sizes,
which made choosing
Top Gear's Best Value Car difficult,
but not impossible!
♪ "Sun Is Shining (De Luxe Edit)"
Funkstar De Luxe
Here are the runners-up.
Skodas are no longer
laughing matters.
The Octavia is practical,
offers superb choice,
and were it not for
the bulletproof build quality,
you'd hear it groaning
under the weight of extras.
Not bad for £ 9,800.
Korea, the country's got soul
but the cars haven't.
However, the Daewoo Tacuma
could change all that.
Starting at a bargain £ 12,500,
it offers the joy of Mini MPV ownership
at a fraction of the price of its rivals.
Also in the running was
the Subaru Impreza WRX.
In a country where you need to
remortgage before vegetable shopping,
the Japanese should
be very proud of this.
At £ 21,495, it's the most affordable
performance car ever.
In the end, those three
came close, but no cigar.
The winner of the Top Gear
Best Value Car award is...
the SEAT León!
♪ "Brown Paper Bag (feat. Dynamite MC)"
Roni Size / Reprazent
SEAT have emptied out
the parts bin of parent Volkswagen,
and stuck together the best bits
with more imagination and spark
than any modern day V-Dub
could possibly hope for.
Buying under ten grand used to have all the glamour of a drug problem.
What little money you had it's gone,
nobody wants to know you anymore,
and your best friend
becomes the local dealer.
Well, the 1.4 S has changed all that.
Twin airbags, ABS, power steering,
and electric front windows,
mean you'd have to go
a long way north of that price
to get anything like the same package.
If you go for this, the entry-level 1.4 S,
you're going to love its easygoing nature.
And those tightwad diesel fanatics
who plump for the 1.9L TDI
are gonna stop pinching their pennies,
and start pinching themselves.
But it's the drivers who go
for the top-of-the-range Cupra,
who will be laughing
all the way to the bank,
and via the long route,
if they've got any sense.
At £14,995, it's a world cruise
cheaper than its close
and more sluggish
relation, the Golf GTI.
And, in comparison,
it drives like a full blooded bull run.
Okay, it's not up to Ford Focus
levels of entertainment,
but brimming with pace
and kit, it doesn't have to be.
♪ "Once Around The Block"
Badly Drawn Boy
Now, here's the thing,
this is, actually, the quickest car you
can buy for under 15 thousand quid.
The turbo knocks out 180 BHP
and it gets from nought
to 60 in just 7.5 seconds.
SEAT say "Enjoy yourself",
and at this price,
with this performance,
I'm on the verge of being
whipped into a veritable frenzy.
No, I am.
The León range
provides a brilliant alternative
to cars with bloated
reputations and price tags,
whether you're a
budget shopper or a boy racer.
Cheap, cheerful and honest fun,
the SEAT León is
Top Gear's Best Value Car for 2001.
Let's face it, scrimping and
saving and worrying about
the pound in your pocket
can be absolute torture.
So do yourself a
favour, stop saving
and start dreaming.
Who wants to be a millionaire
when you can dream
of being a billionaire?
♪ "At The River"
Groove Armada
So, what will you choose
to get around your dream world?
Well, this isn't a bad start.
A 75 foot super yacht, ideal for
taking you from A to B via the Bahamas.
The cost of this high life on the
ocean waves? Well, the sky is the limit.
♪ "Forever Texas"
Robbie Williams
Unless, of course, you've got
one of these at your disposal.
A Sikorsky S-76,
the Rolls-Royce of the skies.
In here it's like an
executive boardroom,
only you're guaranteed
to go up in the world.
So, with sea and air taken care of,
how would you get about on land?
When it comes to choosing
the fleet to fill your fantasy garage,
only the most exclusive cars will do.
So, here are our suggestions, should
you ever stumble across that blank check.
♪ "The Force of Destiny: Overture"
Royal Philharmonic Orchestra
The first of our nominees
is the Ferrari 360 Spider.
The fastest way I
know to top up your turn.
It's ideal when the most important
thing in your life is simply to be seen.
Now, for a Sunday
outing with mum and dad,
what could be more perfect
than a Bentley Arnage Red Label?
You're not so much giving them a lift,
as checking them into a very
expensive hotel. And with 400 BHP,
you could take them
to lunch at the Ritz in Paris
and still be back
home in time for tea.
♪ "Dancing In The Moonlight"
Toploader
Now, when the most important thing
in your life is simply to be heard,
there's the TVR Speed 12.
Loud enough to bring
down birds in light aircraft,
it's perfect for impressing
your mates down the pub.
Listen right, my XR2
is putting out 200 BHP
at the front wheels,
what's yours got?
800.
Isn't it?
But the vehicle with more
global cachet than anything else,
and the winner of the Top Gear
award for the Ultimate Dream Car is...
the £150,000 Lamborghini Diablo.
♪ "Better Man"
Robbie Williams
Its roots lie in an
exotic era, but these
days its performance
lives mainly in fantasy land.
The 6-litre V12,
according to the brochure,
will do more than 205
miles an hour, whilst
0-60 takes, well, just a couple
of turns of those 18 inches.
Even pootling in a
Diablo is a real occasion.
Your body sits deep
in the sculpted seats,
your feet rest on
the tiny race-like pedals,
and your hands wrap around
a bull-embossed leather steering wheel.
The gear change is a
divinely muscular movement
and the steering is
the exact opposite.
However, there is a
Grand National being run back there,
with every one of the 550
horses wanting to win the race.
Believe me,
this is naughtily noisy.
All Diablos come
with attitude as standard.
Sandwich one between a pair of Ferraris
and the Lambo will be the most lusted after.
You see, they're just so exclusive.
♪ "Who Knows Where The Time Goes?"
Fairport Convention
Not so long ago,
200-mile-an-hour motors
seemed to grow on trees,
but this monstrous mid-engine beast
is one of the few remaining examples
of a proud breed, the supercar.
That's what makes it so special.
The stuff dreams are
made of, you bet, and
outrageous ones at that.
The Lamborghini Diablo
wins the Top Gear Award
for the Ultimate Dream Car.
Of course the Lamborghini Diablo is a
dream car, it costs more than a house.
But what about
the people whose job it is
to turn everyday cars
into something desirable?
Yes, the wheelers and
dealers of dreams, the advertisers.
Here's Top Gear's
award for the best car ad.
In fifth place, Audi,
who've come over all trendy
and employed a weight-border
to help them advertise.
Now, are they saying the Quattro's
system is godlike and walks on water?
Or are they trying to say the A6
handles like a big old barge?
Fourth place is taken by Fiat
with their latest advert for the Punto,
which ably demonstrates
what a good shopping car it is.
If you live on the wrong
side of Krakatoa, that is.
Right. If you think
you can do any better,
- You drive.
- Fine.
Look at the mess
you made to the car.
So after the drama of
crashing waves and the
magnificence of an
erupting volcano,
which bit of nature do
VW use in their ads?
A muddy puddle
and a dirty dog. Right.
Good ad, though.
- This one here, Dixon Road?
- Dixon Road, yes.
- Tenner will do it?
- Oh, yes.
Thank you.
BARLOW: Peugeot takes second place
thanks to magician David Blaine.
Can you see the cards?
'Cause I want you to try
to think of one card from
inside, not this one,
look closely, try to see
one. Did you see one?
It might have been
too fast, I'll do it again.
Try to see one card
from inside, not that one.
Don't say it, but you have
one, hold it in your mind.
I know this is not your card,
this is not it, but I want you to visualize
your card right here, see it in
your mind, see it right here.
BARLOW: Now that
is magic, Mr Daniels.
This is not a trick.
- The Peugeot 206 GTI.
- Magic, magic, magic.
- Now you see it,
now you don't.
BARLOW: But the winner
had to be Land Rover,
with the release of their
Freelanders into the wild.
It's an excellent ad that
works on lots of levels.
It makes the car look good,
it makes you think about the brand
and best of all, it lets you
brush up on your Swahili.
Who would have thought, eh?
Here on the edge of the M25...
stands the future,
the Millenium House,
designed to be the perfect
family residence. How?
Well, according
to its architects,
it combines innovation,
technology and environmental
awareness to make family
life that bit more tolerable.
So, there's a lawn on the roof,
which literally cleans the air.
The fridge uses less power than a
light bulb. And there's a dual stage,
extra powerful
programmable flush on the toilet,
for those occasions when...
when... when you get...
I think you get my drift.
So, the perfect family have their perfect
house, but what's their perfect car?
We first met the future in 1984,
courtesy of the Renault Espace.
♪ "I Wanna Be Like You"
Big Bad Voodoo Daddy
The latest version has
great engines and loads of space.
If you've been particularly
carefree when it comes to
family planning,
then it's ideal.
Otherwise, it's almost
too much of a good thing.
So try an Estate instead,
and there's really
none better than the Volvo V70.
It's got a boot so big
it crosses time zones,
and it's packed
with standard equipment.
In T5 form, you'll also be
the coolest parents in the street,
but a very long Volvo is unlikely
to set next door's curtains twitching.
Whereas a Chrysler
PT Cruiser will.
It'll turn your driveway
into 50's America at a stroke,
and then you'll head off,
not on a day trip,
but on a cruise instead.
Which will be fine,
because this is the one American
car that actually drives well.
But despite those crazy looks,
it isn't quite versatile enough.
Our winner, though, and
Top Gear's Best Family Car for 2001
most definitely is versatile enough.
♪ "You See the Trouble With Me"
Black Legend
Yep, it's the Fiat Multipla.
The car that turns as many
stomachs as it does heads.
♪ "Groovejet (If This Ain't Love)"
Black Legend
Oh, please stop groaning,
this thing is quite brilliant.
And what's more,
I'm going to prove it.
We loved the funny Fiat
when we first drove it.
It was new, but more
importantly, it looked new.
We had no hesitation in making it
our Family Car of the Year for 2000,
and despite it scaring the animals,
we made it last year's overall
Car of the Year as well.
Yes, it's that good.
The question is, why have
we got such faith in this car?
Well, believe it or not, it isn't
really all that weird or wacky.
No, it's actually the most
sensible car available today.
Let's look at the evidence.
♪ "I Get The Sweetest Feeling"
Jackie Wilson
The Multipla proves
that six into one does go.
And unlike other MPVs at full capacity,
there's still enough room
left over for the weekly shop.
But it doesn't cheat
by being as long as a Trin.
In fact, it's noticeably
shorter than a Ford Focus,
which means that you can wave goodbye
to touch parking, if that's your bag.
Right, brace yourselves,
we're going in.
Yes, the interior of the Multipla
is even more difficult...
to get your head around than
the exterior. We can't deny it.
But crucially, it all works
brilliantly. Primary colours,
big, chunky, easy to use instruments
and Ribena-friendly fabrics
make for an atmosphere of fun.
In fact, it's not so much
a car, more of a cartoon.
[cartoon sound effects]
♪ The closer you get ♪
♪ The better you look, baby ♪
♪ The better you look,
the more I want you ♪
And as for those looks,
well, let me tell you,
on the continent where
they invented the word 'chic',
this ugly duckling has become
something of a fashion accessory.
The Fiat Multipla
doesn't drive like a van,
it doesn't heave or wallow
through the corners,
and if your precious
little mites decide to use it
as a jungle gym, it won't
go weak at the knees.
If you've got a family, nothing
else does the job quite so well,
or with quite so much imagination.
So there you go.
Unequivocally, the Fiat Multipla
is our Family Car of the Year for 2001.
What do you mean you're still
not convinced? Well, it's your loss.
♪ "Novio"
Moby
NEDDELL: Time for
the penultimate award,
the Best Driver's Car.
Exquisite handling isn't enough,
the winner needs to be equally
at home crossing continents
as scorching round circuits.
But we've imposed a £50,000 price limit,
so you can forget all your
supercars, like this Porsche 911.
Yet the shortlist is still
pretty mouthwatering
and our contenders come
in all shapes and sizes.
♪ "Local Boy In The Photograph"
Stereophonics
There's a hatchback, a saloon,
a sports car and a coupe.
The judging isn't going to
be easy, but it will be fun.
Nowadays, hot hatches are
most people's introduction
to high performance motoring.
And this Renault Sport Clio 172
is a very serious proposition indeed.
Not only has it beat
every other hot hatch around,
its performance embarrasses so much
more expensive machinery as well.
With its nimble handling
and racy interior,
it is a very tempting choice.
But once you've tasted
the sensitive feel of a good rear
wheel drive, you know it just can't win.
♪ "Sing It Back"
Moloko
So what about this four wheel
drive Mitsubishi Evo 6,
forged in the World Rally Championship
to cope with everything
from frozen Finnish lakes
to dusty African deserts?
It's outrageous rubber
ripping fun on an open racetrack,
but its frantic
turbocharged power deliver
and ever varying degrees
of both understeer and oversteer
make it manic
rather than magnificent.
So how about the TVR Tuscan?
380 homemade horsepower,
superb good looks.
Lots of nice quirky little
touches everywhere you look.
Plus, a best-of-both-worlds
removable hard top
and the most stylish interior
on the market today.
British through and through,
I'd love it to be our winner,
but it's just a little bit
too much of a bulldog
for that rewarding yet
restful drive we're looking for.
Which brings us to last year's
Best Driver's Car, the BMW M Coupe.
♪ "Sunset (Bird of Prey)"
Fatboy Slim
It still provides the most relaxed
on the edge motoring available today,
complete with a silken
straight-six power plant
and undeniably eye-catching looks.
And it definitely would have been
our winner if we hadn't discovered this.
The Noble M12.
On the outside it has
the looks of a supercar.
♪ "Finished Symphony"
Hybrid
And on the inside it feels like a supercar,
with this strikingly sculptured dash
threatening warp speed
before you even move.
There's one thing, though,
that's not like a supercar. It's price tag.
At just under £45,000, it's half
that of a Ferrari 360 or 911 Turbo.
The brainchild of one man
and his shed, Lee Noble,
is a rare example of a British
sports car dream come true.
Production's now underway
and first deliveries
are due in the summer.
It's powered by a 2.5 litre Ford V6
which doesn't sound that special,
but twin turbos, 310 horsepower,
and 60 in a nats over four seconds does.
Those turbos progressively boost the power
while their whooshing
and wheezing really get you
in the mood for the best bit.
The handling.
The steering is one of the best
I've ever experienced
and you can consistently
put the front wheels...
exactly where you want to.
If you do turn into a corner a bit too
quickly, the rear of the car will slide out.
But it all happens with so much
feel that even an eight year old
would naturally correct it and
power slide out of the corner.
The M12 is as equally at home
going for a long distance cruise
as it is attacking a race track.
It may only be a two-seater,
but there's plenty of tailored luggage
space so touring is no problem at all.
Monte Carlo, here we come.
The Noble M12 GT is Top Gear's
Best Driver's Car for 2001.
And so, to the announcement of
Top Gear's Car of the Year for 2001.
Now, it's nothing that you have seen
in the last 30 minutes, because
excelling in a single category
just isn't quite enough.
No, Top Gear's Car of the Year
has to be a consummate all-rounder.
But before we reveal the winner,
have a look at what it had to beat.
Cars like the dinky Audi A2.
It's as much of a trinket
as it is a town car.
It is extremely economical, and
it was built by robots who actually care.
But, as our Car of the Year proves,
you don't have to buy German
to guarantee good build quality.
NEEDELL: Our next runner up,
the BMW X5, defies the laws of physics.
It's the first 4x4 that handles
like a car and a sports car at that.
But prices start at £33,000
and that's a bit on the steep side.
Whereas our overall winner is a
touch more attainable from £14,595.
Now, the Honda Civic isn't really fun,
nor is it particularly good looking.
It's just so clever, so sensible,
so reliable and so versatile.
Mind you, all of those things apply
to our Car of the Year as well.
For 99% of the time, our winner would do
absolutely everything you asked of it.
♪ "Don't Tell Me"
Madonna
BUTLER-HENDERSON: The new
Subaru Impreza could have
been a car of the year,
if its looks hadn't divided opinion.
You either hate
them or despise them.
But believe me, four door saloons
have never been so much fun.
Which is pretty true
for our Car of the Year.
It's no rally machine but nevertheless
offers a lively, entertaining drive.
When it comes to the environment,
motor manufacturers
have a conscience too.
Particularly those
brainy boffins at Toyota.
This Prius is a four-seater saloon,
which combines
a super clean electric motor
with a very fuel-efficient petrol one.
It's all very clever but perhaps
more a car for next year than this.
♪ "Saltwater"
Chicane
NEEDELL: So, what is the
Top Gear Car of the Year for 2001?
BUTLER-HENDERSON: It's something
that combines the best qualities
of the other nominees
in just one package.
BARLOW: It's all things to all men.
It's the Ford Mondeo.
What appeals to me
is the way it drives.
This Mondeo hasn't been
engineered by faceless accountants,
but by enthusiasts, making
those everyday journeys
that bit more fun.
But, perhaps most significantly
is what this means for Ford.
Along with the Puma and the Focus,
this is their third Top Gear
Car of the Year award.
Somebody, somewhere is
making the right decisions.
But the fight back
has already begun.
Renault, Citroën and Volkswagen
are all gunning for the Mondeo.
Find out how they get on when the new
series of Top Gear starts on February 22nd.
For now though, we'll let the
Mondeo have its moment of glory.