In tonight's Top Gear
from the Welsh forests,
Volvo's upmarket
new hatchback, the 440.
They're catching the car,
but who was the driver?
And how can you improve on
the ultimate status symbol?
Hello and welcome to Top Gear.
We're at Dinas Mawddwy in deepest
Wales for the Audi Sport Rally.
Only a national event, but
it draws in a world-class field
because it's the last major event before the Lombard RAC,
the British run, of course, of the World Rally Championship,
so it gives the champions a chance
to get to grips with the mud
and the gravel of the British forests.
We'll be looking at some of the rally
teams later on, but while we're tackling
the early stages, let us look at a new car.
Now, the Volvo 340 has been
around for some time, of course,
and it's one of the great unsung
success stories of the car market.
It isn't the prettiest car in the world,
it's underpowered, doesn't handle that well
but it goes on selling,
particularly in this country,
mainly perhaps because
of its reliability and its safety.
But now the Dutch factory of Volvo
have brought out a new model, the 440.
It sits above the 340 in the range,
although it costs a great deal more,
and Chris Goffey has been
to Holland to try it out.
GOFFEY: Volvo's new 440
is a logical development
from the 480 sports car
they launched last year.
It's basically a saloon version of that car
with the same chassis and running gear.
However, adding a saloon superstructure to
the 480 has produced a slightly odd look.
To my mind, the wheels seem too small
for the rather dumpy-looking body shell.
Behind the Volvo badge on the front of
this 440 and on the old 340 series cars is
a completely different factory to the
Swedish Volvo that makes the 7 series and
the 240 Estates.
This is the Dutch concern
that used to make the old rubber band
Variomatic transmission DAFs,
and the Swedish company
only has a 30% stake in this factory.
The British importer admits that he has
to do completely separate marketing deals
with the Dutch and the Swedes.
But that said, there's no way that this
new 440 cashes in on a Volvo image
it doesn't deserve.
There's been tremendous attention to
safety, as you'd expect with a Volvo.
Front and rear ends are crushable,
and there's an immensely
strong passenger cage.
This is the turbo version at the top of
the engine range offered on the 440.
The engines themselves are built by
Renault, and while they're close to the
Renault 21 unit in most aspects,
Volvo insists they're manufactured to
their own specifications.
While there's a lot of headroom in the
440, you feel that the seats are placed
close to the floor
of the car to achieve it.
There's plenty of luggage space
under the hatchback,
and the folding rear seats
are split asymmetrically.
This car was fitted with one of these
dreadful skinny space savers.
I hope the British importer goes for a
proper spare.
There's plenty of room for it.
On the road, this Volvo 440
is a brisk performer.
There's very little road or wind noise.
The handling is precise,
safe and reassuring.
This model's fitted with power steering as
standard, and it gives you a very good
feel of what's going on at the front wheels.
Very impressive that
despite being a turbo car,
there's very little fight
or torque steer at the wheel.
Even when you apply
full power on damp surfaces,
and the front wheels scrabble for grip.
Anti-lock brakes are an option.
A pity they're not standard.
But it's nice to see Volvo have gone for
clear and traditional dials rather than
fashionable digital readouts.
The real crunch will come
for the 440 in Britain
when it goes on sale here next year.
The importers are emphatic that the car is
not a replacement for the old 3 Series,
but will move up into the class above.
They're talking about the
Volkswagen Passat, the Audi 80,
the top-of-the-line Ford Sierra, and the new
Vauxhall Cavalier as the car's competitors,
I'm not sure people
will perceive the car in that class.
To me, it still looks very much an
Escort-sized package, and if that's how
potential 440 customers see it,
Volvo may have problems.
Their owners have always appreciated
a lot of metal for their money,
and the company may have
to work hard in the UK
to convince people
they're still getting it.
So to sum up, the Volvo 440 Turbo
we've been testing
has a 1721 cc engine, developing 118 BHP.
That takes it from 0 to 60 in under 9
seconds, and on to a claimed top speed of
125 miles an hour.
It won't be available in the UK
until spring of next year,
when fuel consumption figures
and prices will be published.
Now, we're sometimes
criticized on this programme
for talking too much about cars' top speeds.
We do talk about them, of course,
but it's worth saying in mitigation,
it's not because of any
glorification of speed as such.
We talk about speed because it's a very
good way of defining a car's performance.
Now, the fact of the matter is
that the performance of most cars
with modern technology
is steadily being improved.
There aren't many family cars,
for example, that can't do 100 mph or more.
And, of course, the temptation is there,
once the performance is there,
to use it as often as possible.
So, greater speeds, on crowded
roads, means greater danger.
And that's why the police are
experimenting with more efficient ways
of catching the lawbreaker.
From a distance, this looks
like any other Jaguar.
But take a look inside,
and it's a police motorway patrol car
with the latest video camera on board.
Any driver thought to be driving
dangerously can be recorded on tape.
Perhaps the first he knows
of it being the blue light
flashing in his rearview mirror.
The driver can then be stopped,
and the tape played back to him.
- Can you stand by the officer here?
Just watch the screen, he will explain
everything to you, alright?
But the motorist isn't always stopped.
In the case of cars that go through
traffic lights on the red,
a camera can be installed
to take photographs automatically.
In fact, two are taken.
The first is triggered as the car
goes through the red light.
The second proves that the car
actually crossed the junction.
Now, there is another technique
the police have been experimenting with
in various parts of the country.
It's a stills camera linked to
a very accurate radar beam
that can read a car's speed
virtually instantaneously.
So the equipment is set up
on the side of the road
without the law having to be present.
Whenever a car goes through
the beam above the speed limit,
the camera automatically takes
a photograph of it and prints out the speed,
and the date and the time as well.
So imagine the deterrent effect of that.
Photographic boxes set up alongside the
road, motorways and ordinary roads,
they wouldn't all have cameras in them,
but you wouldn't know
which ones didn't have.
So whenever you drove past
one above the speed limit,
you'd run the risk of being photographed.
Now, all the equipment we've been talking
about has been used in some countries
for several years now.
It's become a regular part
of traffic law enforcement.
But there are still several problems over
the use of this equipment in this country.
At the present time, every time
we take someone to court
for the offense of excess speed,
we need to have a police officer
who will state that the vehicle
was exceeding the speed limit and
that is corroborated by other means.
With the automatic camera, it requires
no human input whatsoever.
After setting the limits, it will keep
taking the photographs
of speeding vehicles as they go by.
The general view is that currently,
in the case of speeding,
photographic evidence taken
using automatic equipment
without a policeman being present
isn't valid in the courts
and therefore can't be used on its own.
There are other problems.
For example, under current law,
the police can't send prosecution notices
of speeding through the post.
They actually have to visit the driver.
So if the new equipment were introduced,
meaning many thousands
more offenders were caught,
it would mean a massive increase
in workload for the police and could even
clog up the courts with motoring cases.
It raises the whole question of actually
pinning down who was driving the vehicle
at the time the offence was committed.
- Putting to one side
fixed penalty offenses
of not displaying
an excise license or parking,
the police have got to prove
not only that an offense has been committed,
but the person charged committed it.
So they will normally send to a
registered keeper, a piece of paper saying,
please tell us who was driving
at the time of the offense.
He commits an offense if
he doesn't, and he could say,
but he can't get his license
endorsed for that.
But if he owns up and says it was me,
he will get his license endorsed.
There's not, under a present law,
much of an incentive to him
to own up and say it was me.
So if the police write to the owner
asking for the name of the driver
and the owner refuses to cooperate,
he wouldn't receive
penalty points on his license.
But just how much effort will the police
expend in trying to identify the driver?
- Depends on the circumstances.
If it's a very serious case, then we
may follow it up with a visit
to the registered owner or ask
an adjoining police force to visit him.
But of course, there has
to be a cut-off point.
- In terms of effort alone?
- In terms of effort.
Our efforts are towards enforcing the
speed limit and bringing people to justice.
And we would have to weigh
the pros and cons of a particular case
before we went even further.
This begins to challenge, perhaps,
the fundamental principle
of innocence until proved guilty.
But there are wider implications
brought into the equation,
the infringement of civil liberties.
We welcome a system
which records offenders accurately.
But our concern is that we should have a
system which isn't also open to abuse.
For instance, for the police monitoring
the whereabouts of citizens
as they travel around the country.
And it seems to us that it is a case of
technology developing far more rapidly
than any safeguards to protect the public.
And is crying out for legislation
to build those safeguards in.
So, where does that leave us?
Well, the report of the North Committee that
was set up recently to examine traffic law
came out with three
unequivocal recommendations.
They were that photographs
taken by automatic cameras
should be acceptable in court
as evidence of speeding.
That the penalty for not cooperating with
the police in revealing the name of the driver
should be increased to include
three penalty points in the license.
And finally, the police should be allowed
to send fixed penalty type notices
through the post for speeding offenses.
And so, cut out a lot of police paperwork
and help to unclog the courts.
But if these recommendations
do come into force,
what happens if the owner
doesn't know who the driver was?
In, for example, the case of a company
pool car used by several different drivers.
- Well, if the registered keeper doesn't
know, or he can't remember, you know,
your worships it was a month ago,
how can I possibly say now?
Then he would be acquitted.
There's no question of a conviction.
But if a court thinks he's telling
a pack of lies, he'd be convicted
and penalty points
will be awarded against him.
- The implications of these potential
changes seem disturbing.
The owner of the vehicle seeming
guilty until proven innocent.
But, of course, that has to be balanced
against the widespread concern
to reduce the deaths and injuries
on our roads each year.
Meanwhile, back here
at the Audi Sport Rally,
speed is, of course, the essence,
trimming that last tenth of a second of
the time in the special stages.
It's the last round of
the National Rally Championship,
so it's a big event in its own right.
But it's come to resemble a world-class event
because, as I said, so many of the
top world stars use it as a practice
under British conditions before
the rigours of the Lombard RAC.
All eyes were on the
four-wheel drive Toyota Celica
in the hands of former
Ford driver Jimmy McRae.
It's the most likely car to beat the
all-conquering Lancia team next month.
Lancia have literally
swept the board this year
and had the World Championship
sewn up by June in America.
So there wasn't much point in them
turning up for the Audi Sports.
At the moment, Lancia lead Ford by nearly
70 points on the table, an astonishing lead.
Audi are still in the frame,
thanks to the efforts of privateers,
with Mazda trailing a poor fourth.
McRae was putting up some
very fast times in the Toyota,
even though it was the first
time he'd driven it in anger.
But then came problems.
- Well, the last two miles in the
last stage, we had no rear brakes
and we were taking it pretty easy.
But I think it's a good job that happened
because the front diff has gone
and it's burst the casing of the gearbox.
So, I mean, it takes about an
hour and a half to change it.
So we've decided that we're
not going to go any further.
The lads will go back, change the gearbox
and we'll get on with some
serious testing next week.
I mean, I was learning to drive the thing
and everybody was learning about the car.
So we're quite confident
that the car is competitive.
We'll just go away now
and sort it out on our own.
MASON: Mazda have had a dreadful year
with a whole chapter of mechanical failures,
quite often related to the engine.
But mostly we have had engine problems.
And we are having 1,600 engines and it's a
little bit too small for this job.
And we have to try to get all the power
out of it, what we can get.
And, of course, that expense of
reliability sometimes.
MASON: Former world
rally champions Mikkola and Salonen
were again let down by their Mazdas,
engines and rear suspension this time.
Not a good omen for the Lombard RAC.
Ford beat Lancia earlier this year
on the all-tarmac Corsican rally,
but their two-wheel drive
will be a problem in November.
For veteran Stig Blomqvist, the Audi Sport was a chance
to prove that he hadn't lost his speed,
but he could only manage
second place, poor by his standards.
But would you ever believe that this
Sierra went on to win its class?
Making its debut on this rally was
Vauxhall's new 16-valve engine,
but still only two-wheel drive.
Will this be a disadvantage?
Well, it's a big disadvantage
probably on the RAC, yes,
because it tends to be very muddy and wet...
But hopefully, as I say, this will
definitely put us in the reckoning with
all the other two-wheel drive
cars on the rally.
- Aren't Vauxhall just sort of treading water
for the moment, ready for the Cavalier 4x4?
- Well, that's right. I mean,
this car uses the same engine
as what we'll probably be
using in the Cavalier 4x4
so it's a good experience to get mileage
and et cetera on this particular engine.
And obviously we're very
excited and looking forward
to this new car that's coming.
MASON: The new engine
came up with the goods.
Wilson set a scorching pace,
beating many four-wheel drive cars
to achieve third place overall.
Coventry's Peugeot team has
to combine its activities to Britain,
but has been going great guns this year,
headed by the world's leading lady rally driver, Louise Aitken-Walker.
Seventh on this rally,
she showed her magnificent drive
on last year's Lombard RAC
was no flash in the pan.
Among the most unusual cars on the Audi
Sport was this tiny Nissan March Turbo.
Nothing to do with March racing cars,
just a hotted-up version
of the Nissan Micra.
Under the bonnet,
there's a tiny 988cc engine.
This has been given a turbocharger,
so it produces 130 brake horsepower.
And so you can see that the Japanese
have actually found a way
of putting a quart into a pint pot.
Inside, it has all the rally car
trappings, including a six-speed gearbox
that looks a little like an oil rig.
Why aren't you driving a proper rally car?
- What bloody hell you mean?
No, it's a good car.
OK, this is a very small car.
This is really the smallest rally car,
I think, in the Sport now.
And the reason is that people in Japan,
Nissan, like to try this car in rallying.
This is, you can say, a club car in Japan.
And we try to prove that you
can even rally with a small car.
MASON: But never
underestimate Per Eklund.
The jolly Swede pushed the Nissan
ahead of many more powerful cars.
Another surprise of the rally
was the performance of Ian Roberton.
His old Nissan 240 charged round the route
to clinch the British
National Championship.
He beat many more exotic
machines into the bargain.
But at the head of the field, the vastly
experienced Russell Brooks
was showing a return to splendid form,
beating Blomqvist by nearly two minutes.
The old Brooks magic was still there,
so the Sierras could still be a force
to be reckoned with
in November's big rally.
And maybe Russell's
old adversary, Jimmy McRae,
will regret his move from Ford to Toyota.
- We shall be reporting on the
Lombard RAC with two programmes,
one early evening, one late,
on each of the four days.
Now to something which rally
cars tend not to suffer from
because they're worked on so
intensively. I'm talking about rust.
Cars are certainly better made these days
and therefore they tend
to suffer from rust less.
The Swedes, for example, have
carried out lots of surveys in this area
and they've shown the
average life of most cars,
their average durability
is steadily improving.
However, whether a car will rust
or not is certainly a major factor
in deciding whether or not to buy.
That's why, of course, many manufacturers
are now giving anti-rust guarantees.
The question is, do they stand up?
Tom Boswell has been casting his
microscope over the fine print of these
guarantees to see just
how watertight they are.
BOSWELL: Rust is the
dread of the car industry.
Not so long ago, several manufacturers
gained reputations for producing models
which rusted faster than others.
Alfa Romeo, Datsun, Ford, Renault
and Talbot, to name but a few.
A rusty image isn't easily shaken off
and sales can be drastically affected,
as Lancia discovered
in the 70's with their Beta.
Now manufacturers give far more
consideration to prevention
with improved paints and primers.
More attention is paid to vulnerable areas
with plastic, wax or other coatings.
Additions such as wheel arch
liners give extra protection.
Some even use galvanized panels.
The majority then back this up with
some form of anti-corrosion warranty.
These last from typically around
six years up to ten years
and Volvo recently have even
introduced a form of lifetime cover.
Linda Zeff is one of several owners
who feel they've been misled.
Her car was just four years old
when she first noticed rust.
- Well, when I bought the car, it came
with a six-year anti-rust warranty.
And I took that to mean that the car
wouldn't rust within six years,
or if it did, the company would repair it.
And it developed patches of rust
and I took it in just over a year ago for
its anti-rust check, its annual check.
And was told that these particular patches
of rust weren't covered by the warranty
because this rust was rusting from the
outside in and not from the inside out
and therefore wasn't covered.
And obviously it's got
slightly worse since then.
- Did you read the rust guarantee?
- No, I didn't.
I assumed that the company was offering
something that was worth having.
It didn't occur to me that they were
offering something that had so many
clauses or get-out clauses.
BOSWELL: Most warranties refer
to perforation or rust-through.
This means a hole which
has rusted from the inside.
Rusting on the outside surface from
scratches or stone chips isn't covered.
If it's not repaired at your expense,
the warranty can become useless.
The most straightforward of these
anti-corrosion warranties include those
offered by Ford, Audi VW and Vauxhall.
They require no special re-treatments or
inspections, both common conditions.
Otherwise, it's up to the owner
to ensure the car is presented on time
for each and every inspection.
This usually is once a year,
sometimes with a period of
latitude as little as 14 days.
Washing the car may also be a
requirement for which you have to pay.
When an inspection's carried out,
the paperwork's most important.
For example, Mitsubishi state:
"You must ensure...
that the periodic body inspection record
is properly stamped and signed."
Re-treatments are required
by many companies.
They're usually needed at the
first, third and fifth years,
and it can cost up to £50.
Wear and tear doesn't just affect
the polished surfaces.
Rusting due to scrapes, scratches and
chips underneath must be repaired,
again, at your expense.
And that's not the end of the small print.
There can be some rather vague clauses.
Fiat stipulates: "Check and
clean the vehicle regularly."
"Keep the engine compartment clean."
"Check and clear all drainage holes
at the base of the door frames."
But what's meant by regularly?
And when did you last
check your drain holes?
Fiat say "the care and maintenance
instructions are a sensible precaution to
"prevent the neglect and abuse of a vehicle
and have never in fact been used to
"invalidate the anti-perforation warranty."
Accidental damage must be repaired
to manufacturer's specifications.
If you apply your own
rust proofing to damaged areas,
again, you're in danger
of ruining that warranty.
Besides Top Gear, the Consumers'
Association is also concerned
about rust warranties.
- They're very variable.
Some manufacturers are setting the pace
with very good guarantees
that require no inspections
and don't cost the customer anything.
Others are lagging a long way behind that.
And really could make
the thing much simpler.
And they really should be
guaranteeing their product
rather than depending on the customer
to do half the work for them.
- Are they using their small
print in their guarantees
to hide behind problems of their cars?
- Well, it's difficult to tell how much
that's happening, but certainly a lot of
local agents seem to make it very
difficult for the customer to actually get
a resolution of the problem.
When the local garage backs the customer
and takes the problem to the manufacturer,
generally things seem to
get sorted out very quickly.
But it's all to do with
customer relations and
actually wanting the
customer to get a good deal.
And not everybody in the system at the
moment is doing that well enough.
BOSWELL: Our advice is to read
the warranty yourself before you buy.
If you have a problem, complain early
and stick to the same dealer.
And as the Fiat warranty
now suggests, if all else fails,
approach the manufacturer directly
or go to an independent arbitrator.
One car that doesn't carry a rust warranty
is, would you believe, the Rolls-Royce.
No doubt they think it's beneath them
because, of course, a six-year-old
Rolls-Royce is scarcely run in.
This is the latest version of the ultimate
status symbol, the Silver Spirit,
£86,000 or new.
For that, you get no fancy extras,
just the standard wrap-around leather,
the worn-up veneer and, of course,
the spirit of ecstasy.
Now, for many people, even this is too
plain a symbol of their power and prestige.
CLARKSON: Customizing has
always been a very dirty word.
You customize a Ford Capri.
You do not customize a modern-day
Bentley or Rolls-Royce.
What Hooper, bespoke coachbuilders
for more than a century do,
is Hooperise them.
Now, this one, for instance, is seriously
lacking in the door department.
It began in life as a pretty standard
Bentley Turbo R with four doors
and has been converted into
what's called a two-door coupé, i.e.
it has one long door on either side.
And that means there's pretty substantial
alterations between here and here.
Moving further forward, you have
colour-coordinated windscreen wipers.
They're very tasty.
And further forward still, we have a
couple of air ducts in the bonnet.
Right at the front, only
the badge escapes attention.
Square headlights will keep
our American friends happy.
And strangely, in a car with the
aerodynamic properties of a wardrobe,
they've seen fit to attach a spoiler
beneath the rouged bumpers.
There's even a natty pair
of skirts along the side.
Finally, it's all topped off with
these polished chrome wheels.
The modified Bentleys and Rolls-Royces
come out of a North London factory
which specializes in fitting its own
bodies to someone else's wheels.
But how do you improve on what's widely
regarded as the best already?
The job's made even harder, because
in order to keep the warranty intact,
all the mechanical
bits and bobs are left alone.
The bodies, however,
most certainly aren't.
They can chop your car in half,
add a four-foot section in the middle,
completely re-equip
the interior, and in the process,
lighten your wallet to the tune
of half a million pounds.
Semi-shake money buys
hand-crafted wooden door cappings,
or maybe some of the endless gizmos.
In fact, they'll do anything a customer
wants, providing they're not asked to
wander off too deeply
into the realms of poor taste.
A Rolls-Royce beach buggy,
for instance, is considered to be
on the wrong side of the borderline.
However, it seems a purple car
with a Dralon interior is not.
- We often fit quite outrageous styles
and colors, but of course that very much
depends on where the car's going
and the environment it's going to be in.
So it's very difficult
for us to take a decision
and say that a particular car
is outlandish or unrealistic.
It's very, very important to be mindful of their particular circumstances.
CLARKSON: So what
are these circumstances?
Well, obviously a great many do
end up in places like Saudi Arabia,
where 24-carat gold-plated everything
is not deemed vulgar.
But a fair few stay at home.
I had a package where they literally
hooperised, as they term it, the vehicle,
from the point of view of the internal
work on walnut veneer,
the various picnic tables
and drinks cabinets.
I had a double CD installed
within the console.
I had the front spoilers of Valance and a
few other external appearances which set
the car apart from other normal
Bentleys and Rolls-Royces.
The Bentley car is a driver's car,
and I just felt that if I wanted a tourer,
whether it's just driving around London
and the South East or going abroad,
then I might as well equip it.
- There's just something
very special about them.
They give us the extra
things that we need.
Not just special colors, but special
things like our back window, which has
been colored slightly because
I don't like the sun too much.
I have a very, very special chauffeur
who looks after the cars
rather as if they're his children.
- Frankly, you can't blame anyone
for treating these cars like children.
I mean, this began in life as one of the
most expensive production cars ever and
now costs, what, two, three times more?
Whether you like the hooperisation
programme or not, remember,
there's still a Bentley turbo underneath.
Somewhere.
Well, if you happen to fancy that Bentley,
you're in luck because it is for sale.
It's only two years old.
It's being offered at £114,000.
Obviously, a mere snip at the price.
That's all for this week.
Next week, we've got a report
on easing traffic congestion,
we look at the latest work
on improving motorcycle safety,
we road test the new Honda Concerto,
and we look at three-wheelers.
So, see you next week.
Same time, same place.
Until then, drive safely. Good night.