♪ "Whole Lotta Love"
Led Zeppelin
Hello and welcome!
Welcome to Top Gear of the Pops!
Now, as I'm sure you know, Top of the Pops
was killed off last year, but they wanted
to bring it back for this Comic Relief
special and we were given the job
because our name is quite similar.
Yeah, so what we've got in store is,
like Top Gear, only half as long.
And instead of cars, there's music.
So we've got Supergrass,
we've got Travis...
Yeah, and then, at the end... right?
At the end of the show,
the three of us will be performing
as a band for the very first time!
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
- Yes!
-Yeah!
We could well...
We could well set a record as the worst
band ever to appear on British television!
Yeah, but that's then, this is now,
and we're kicking off tonight
with the latest single
from Lethal Bizzle.
♪ "Mr."
Lethal Bizzle
♪ Yeah, it's Lethal the Bizzle records ♪
♪ It's Back to Bizznizz ♪
♪ Fire Camp! ♪
♪ It's Lethal the Bizzle records ♪
♪ It's, it's Lethal the Bizzle records ♪
What the fuck is this?
I think Hammond put him
on at the wrong speed!
♪ Imma take your girlfriend
and F your sister, mister ♪
♪ You don't wanna play ♪
♪ Mister, nah ♪
He said he wanted to borrow a hoe!
Well, maybe he's a farmer!
♪ Who do you really
ever think you're talking to? ♪
♪ What do you really think
you really wanna do? ♪
♪ You don't wanna play ♪
♪ Mister, nah ♪
♪ You don't wanna play, mister ♪
♪ Imma take your
girlfriend and F your sis- ♪
[SONG CUTS]
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
What are you doing?
It's noises like that that killed off
Top of the Pops in the first place.
No, it wasn't!
It was!
They were saying "Oh, no-one's
interested in the charts any more,
"Oh, Fearne Cotton's
dress isn't see-through",
and afterwards, they kept
booking acts like, what's his name?
Jizzy Tissue.
Lethal... Lethal Bizzle.
- After that rather truncated first song...
- What have you got next?
Someone rolling a barrel
of spoons down some stairs?
No.
Well, actually, almost.
It's James May!
Right.
Now, to liven up the old
Top of the Pops format,
we've had an idea.
We're going to invite a band on and
we're going to give them a challenge.
Yeah, we're going to ask them
to write an entire song from scratch
and then perform it
at the end of the show.
Yeah, and this sort of thing
will require excellent songwriting skills,
superb musicianship, so
would you please welcome,
ladies and gentlemen, Mc... Fly!
Hello!
Hello.
Welcome to Top Gear of the Pops.
- Now, look...
- You can't be formal with a band!
- OK.
Now...
This is a chance for you to prove
that you're not just some useless,
manufactured, dopey boy band.
Well, we are.
No, you're not.
Well, let's find out, because we know...
that you knew we were
going to ask you to do this
and that you've probably already
worked up a song, haven't you?
We haven't at all. I promise.
Just to make absolutely
sure you can't cheat
and, to be honest,
to bugger you up completely,
we've invented some rules.
- Yeah.
So there are three words that
you can't use in writing your song.
And they are...
Love,
Baby...
and heart.
But there's more.
Because there are three words
that you must use.
And they are...
Sofa.
Sofa?
Administration.
And Hyundai.
What do you think?
You do it?
Can I go?
Yep.
Hyundai.
- Hyundai.
- Absolutely, ok.
Right.
- I'm looking forward to that.
- How long do we have?
Well, you've got until the end
of the show, so if I were you...
I'd bugger off and get cracking.
Yeah, right around.
Good luck, guys.
Hyundai.
Can't wait for that.
Meanwhile, here's a reminder
of why we're all here.
Comic Relief has spent years helping
teenagers who have run away from home and
got into trouble with drink,
drugs, and even prostitution.
Now we want to spend the money to stop
this happening to help the runaways get
home before the trouble begins.
Concern is growing for a 13-year-old girl
from Milton Keynes who's gone missing.
Christy Jay Mahoney
disappeared last Friday night
- Every day I used to think,
is she going to come home?
Will she come back in one piece?
Is she going to come back in a black bag?
My initial first step, get posters
splattered around Milton Keynes,
bus stops, buses, up the city centre.
At the end of the day, it was just a
case of just
trying to find my daughter.
Children who run away can find it hard to
ring home for all sorts of reasons.
But they are in real danger.
That's why the Runaway Helpline
has been set up.
It's for under 18s, it's confidential, and
the operators understand what both
children and parents are going through.
Can you tell me what happened?
Why you left?
They can help find children a safe place
to stay and can help them get back in
touch with their families.
Every day I'd be waiting
on the phone to ring.
Every day was an agonising 24 hours.
After three long weeks, Christy Jay made the
most important call of her life.
She called her mum.
And then when I heard her little voice on
the phone saying, ''Hi, Mum, it's me,
CJ.'' And I said, ''Where are you?''
And she said, ''I'll be home soon.''
And when I saw
Christy Jay at the front door...
I just put my arms around her
and I didn't want to let her go.
There are vulnerable children out there
on the streets tonight in danger,
frightened, confused.
I hope it's not your child.
But projects like the Runaway Helpline,
funded by Comic Relief, are working now to
keep these children safe and we
are asking you to help us to help them.
Help bring families back together where we
can and bring kids to safety before their
lives fall apart.
To make a donation,
telephone 08457 910 910 or you
can log on to bbc.co.uk/rednoseday.
Yes.
Do that.
And now it's time for the news.
We thought what we'd do in
Top Gear of The Pops is blend
kind of musical news and motoring news.
So, you know cars...
- Yes, we know cars...
- Yes, Jeremy, we know cars.
Good.
Well, you know... iPods.
Why can't you plug an iPod into a car?
But you can.
A Mercedes, you can.
I know you can in a Mercedes, and you
can even adjust it on the steering wheel.
But the vast majority of cars that I test,
you can't just plug an iPod in.
Now, everybody's got an iPod these days.
I haven't.
Everybody under 140 years old
has got an iPod these days.
- They are everywhere.
- You've got to remember that the car
industry took 50 years to work out
that a little light needed to
come on when you opened the door.
So I wouldn't hold your breath.
Anyway, okay, right, listen.
Can I just make a plea
to the makers of iPods?
You know the wire thing, okay?
Yes.
You fold it up really neatly,
put it in your pocket, pull it out,
one minute later,
it is a knot so complicated.
- Yeah.
- I'm right.
I've ended up...
If you put your iPod on,
I get the things...
It's just two huge knots.
I know exactly what
you mean. It's immaculately neat.
You pull it out of your pocket
and you'll never undo it.
It's got one of your
testicles tied up in it.
Listen, I've got a story
here about Coldplay.
And I'm really... I'm sorry,
but I don't understand it.
Listen to this. "Fear not, however,
"they haven't gone emo for
the follow-up to the mega 'X&Y'"
What the bloody hell does that mean?
- We work with this all the time.
- It's rubbish.
One of the things I thought we could do
in the news was talk about festivals.
Loads coming up this year, and
I've got the line-ups from some of them.
So, there's Hyde Park Calling.
They've got Aerosmith,
possibly the Rolling Stones.
V Festival. Kasabian, The Fratellis,
Snow Patrol, Basement Jaxx.
Worst band in the world.
- What, Basement Jaxx?
- Basement Jaxx.
- No, why Basement Jaxx?
- No, no, no...
Worst band ever, ever, ever...
to go near a microphone.
No, I...
I'd like to hose them down
with machine gun fire.
Crying out loud.
What do you think of them, James?
I've never had a Basement Jack.
This is like talking to me dad
about music when I was a kid.
I have to say, my dad...
My favourite one my dad did
watching Top Of The Pops was...
What's his name?
Billy Idol came on to do "White Wedding",
and he just looked and he went...
"He had a thought going on telly,
he'd have put a shirt on."
That's what you sound like.
Oh, no, but I have to say, most festivals
these days, I think, are getting a lot better.
I'm going to Glastonbury this year.
- Well, what, presumably...
- Yeah.
in a Range Rover
with a posh Fortnum's hamper?
No.
No, I'm going in a helicopter.
Oh, for crying out loud.
How very, very festival.
But, no, we're going to land
during the Arctic Monkeys,
and that'll improve it for everybody else.
Now, here's a musical
figure, Phil Spector,
a musical name, of course. He's on trial,
he's going to be going on trial
for murdering somebody called
Clarkson.
We've all felt like that
on occasions, obviously.
Yeah.
But he felt it was a good idea,
obviously, to convince the jury
that he's not mental.
So, here's the image he's gone for.
Here's the...
[LAUGHS]
Yeah, yeah, yeah, there
they're going to trust you.
"No, I didn't do anything!"
"Right, no, of course he didn't".
Actually, Jeremy...
Yes, all right, I know it.
I was thinking of stuff
we could talk about.
Lists, that's kind of appropriate, isn't it?
Of records and things.
I love a list.
Right, well, a subject.
You know hospital radio?
Yes.
Well, I don't, you would.
All right.
..with your past in local radio DJing.
Well, a lot of DJs started there, it's relevant.
Well, I've been thinking of a list of songs
that they can't play
on your hospital radio.
Number one:
The Verve, "Drugs Don't Work".
- That'd be difficult to listen to.
- Sure, you can't play that.
What about Cutting Crew,
"I Could Have Died In Your Arms Tonight"?
Fergal Sharkey, "A Good Heart"
could be sensitive in certain wards.
Yeah, for the transplant ward.
- That would not be...
- A good heart is hard to find.
When you think about it, it's perfect.
This is a brilliant idea. Charts.
It's a good chart, innit?
Top five records for playing...
Somewhere.
Yeah, exactly.
Have you seen the
new Snow Patrol video?
No.
Well, and remember "Rendez-vous"?
- Yes.
- That French film director, wasn't it?
And he got a bit of film left and he bolted
the camera to the front of his Ferrari
blasted through the streets of Paris.
- We showed it on Top Gear, didn't we?
- Yeah.
Well, they've put their new track
over the "Rendez-vous" video.
Here it is.
♪ "Open Your Eyes"
Snow Patrol
That is not a bad tune, that.
I like it.
Thing is, though...
Can we just see the original of that?
Because I think the noise
in the original is better.
I mean, it's not a bad tune.
It's a good tune. I like it.
You can hear the words
and everything, but...
Annoyingly, I think you're right.
A Ferrari V12 is better
than Snow Patrol.
Big trend at the moment,
old supergroups reforming.
Genesis, The Police,
Van Halen, apparently...
- No, Van Halen were going...
- Or have they fall out again?
Yeah, they've fallen out.
Well, it's because modern music,
like Jizzy Tissue that we had on earlier...
is such rubbish that that's why
the old ones are getting back to...
No, it's because old farts like you two
keep supporting all these
old bands full of old farts
at festivals in your helicopters,
and that's why they keep going.
Genesis is better than any modern band...
No, they're not, they're old.
You two start...
OK, well, so...
You're only saying you're old as well?
Yeah.
- She is.
- That's inappropriate, unfortunately.
- Why do you think that Genesis is back?
I know Phil Collins.
Phil Collins is not Genesis, woman!
Phil Collins was one of the
best drummers in the world,
and on Selling England by the Pound,
if you listen to "Firth of Fifth",
the drumming in that is...
- Oh, there we go.
- I'm sorry.
Now he's started to ramble
on about the old days.
I suppose you've heard...
I can feel it coming...
Jeremy, you're singing on television.
Stop it immediately.
Right, that is the end
of the news. And now,
I'd like to say that it gives me
great pleasure to introduce the next band,
but since they're performing
a new single we haven't heard yet,
who knows whether
it'll be a pleasure or not.
Anyway, ladies and gentlemen,
please welcome, Travis!
♪ "Closer"
Travis
♪ I've had enough... ♪
♪ of this parade ♪
♪ I'm thinking of the words to say ♪
♪ We open up ♪
♪ Unfinished parts ♪
♪ Broken up ♪
♪ It's so mellow ♪
♪ And when I see you
Then I know it will be next to me ♪
♪ And when I need you
Then I know you will there with me ♪
♪ I'll never leave you ♪
♪ Just need to get closer ♪
♪ Closer ♪
♪ Lean on me now,
lean on me now ♪
♪ Closer, closer ♪
♪ Lean on me now,
lean on me now ♪
♪ Keep waking up ♪
♪ (Waking up) ♪
♪ Without you here ♪
♪ (Without you here) ♪
♪ Another day ♪
♪ (Another day) ♪
♪ Another year ♪
♪ (Another year) ♪
♪ I seek the truth ♪
♪ (I seek the truth) ♪
♪ We set apart ♪
♪ (We set apart) ♪
♪ Second dance ♪
♪ Second chance ♪
♪ (Second chance) ♪
♪ And when I see you
Then I know it will be next to me ♪
♪ And when I need you
Then I know you will there with me ♪
♪ I'll never leave you ♪
♪ Just need to get closer ♪
♪ Closer ♪
♪ Lean on me now,
lean on me now ♪
♪ Closer, closer ♪
♪ Lean on me now,
lean on me now ♪
♪ And when I see you
Then I know it will be next to me ♪
♪ And when I need you
Then I know you will there with me ♪
♪ I'll never leave you ♪
♪ Just need to get closer ♪
♪ Closer ♪
♪ Lean on me now,
lean on me now ♪
♪ Closer, closer ♪
♪ Lean on me now,
lean on me now ♪
♪ Lean on me now ♪
♪ Closer, closer ♪
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
Thanks.
Yes!
Well, I think that was a pleasure.
Very, very tuneful.
Anyway, anyway, it's time now
for the charts from last week!
I'm sorry we don't have this week's charts,
but we're recording this live last Sunday.
Right, here we go.
At five, it's Fray, How To Save a Life.
At four, Grace Kelly, with "MIKA".
At three, it's Akon
featuring The Sweet Escape,
performing "Gwen Stefani".
And at num...
Look, I'm sorry, mate.
What is it now?
Look, I'll tell you what it is now.
The only person who cares
how many records Akon has sold...
is Akon. All we're bothered
about, bearing in mind...
how horrible modern music is
how quickly they get the song over with.
So, I've come up with
a new chart, and here it is.
At number three, it's Kelis featuring
someone with a name
they weren't christened with
and "Lil Star" at
three minutes, 14 seconds.
At number two, Grace Kelly,
who didn't die in a car accident,
as we all suspected,
with "MIKA". Three
minutes, eight seconds.
But the fastest record
in the chart this last week was...
Cascada, with "Miracle".
Two minutes, 46 seconds.
Yes!
Right.
Okay, time for another reminder
of why we're actually here.
Remember Somaliland, I took you on a
nightmare trip once there, to Hargeisa
Hospital, a hospital with no drugs, no
surgical instruments, no sterile equipment.
It was 2003, but you'd think I'd stepped
into a Victorian horror story.
I'd never seen anything like it.
People were turned away because there was
no drugs.
People were turned away from the hospital
because they had no money.
Do you ever wonder what happened to your
money?
Did it do any good?
Did it achieve anything?
You bet it did.
Have a look.
I'm filming for Comic Relief in Kenya,
but I've got hold of some footage that's
just come over the border from Somaliland.
This is our pharmacy.
So this is... You can see all the drugs
are here.
All this is from Comic Relief.
It's remarkable, isn't it?
The drugs have done a lot of good things
in Hargeisa.
Here, everybody can get drugs whether they
pay or not.
That's the best thing I could have seen,
because the people who can't afford the
drugs get them for nothing, which is
absolutely brilliant.
You've set them up forever.
One of the biggest problems
for the hospital was that people
couldn't get there quickly
enough in an emergency.
And those first few minutes can mean the
difference between life and death.
Their only ambulance was literally rusting
into the ground.
Yes!
Isn't that the best?
To see the ambulance all shiny with Comic Relief
on the side and the old siren going there.
Your money bought them a new ambulance.
The difference is absolutely staggering.
I'm blown sideways by this.
Now the wards look a little more familiar.
They're still in desperate need of some
serious attention.
It's just overwhelming to see all you've
done for this hospital.
Your money has provided drugs,
a much needed ambulance, and it's helped
turn this hospital around.
But as you've seen, that's just the start.
And we've still got a long way to go.
With your help, we can fix this ward.
We can finish the job.
Without you, this terrifying thing
happens.
It's called nothing.
Please, give us a call.
And give as much as you can.
You've seen what your money can do.
08457 910 910.
Or donate online at bbc.co.uk/rednoseday.
Thank you.
You can change and save lives today.
Phone that number or we'll tell your
neighbours that you interfere with animals.
Jeremy.
Yes, now it's back to the music.
Our next band, the drummer...
His dad used to be a presenter
on Top Gear about 20 years ago.
Chris Goffey, you may remember him.
Anyway, here they are,
with Ade Edmondson on guitar.
Please welcome, Supergrass!
Right, chaps.
In order to glam this up visually, okay,
the three of us are going to be
providing some special effects for you.
So, Hammond, are you ready on the wind?
- Yeah, I'm ready.
May, are you ready with
the Bonnie Tyler doves?
- Yeah, I think so.
Good, I'm on dry ice.
Start your tune!
♪ "Richard III"
Supergrass
♪ Got up today ♪
♪ What a day! ♪
♪ Thanks a million ♪
♪ Spent too much time
Wondering why I got an opinion ♪
♪ I know you wanna try and get away ♪
♪ But it's the hardest thing ♪
♪ You'll ever know ♪
♪ Waiting in line ♪
♪ Terrible time ♪
♪ Over familiar ♪
♪ We'll take them away ♪
♪ They've nothing to say ♪
♪ They're over the hill, yeah ♪
♪ I know you wanna try and get away ♪
♪ But it's the hardest thing ♪
♪ You'll ever know ♪
♪ Trying to get at you ♪
Adrian Edmonson, everybody!
♪ I know you wanna try and get away ♪
♪ But it's the hardest thing ♪
♪ You'll ever know ♪
♪ I know you wanna try and get away ♪
♪ But it's the hardest thing ♪
♪ You'll ever know ♪
Thank you very much!
CLARKSON: I am so sorry.
I am so sorry, I am so sorry...
Sorry.
- Thank you.
- Sorry.
I am so sorry, chaps.
And what makes it worse is the chicken.
Top Gear Dog has eaten it.
It's a disaster, but
ladies and gentlemen,
a big hand for Supergrass!
- Thank you!
Excellent!
Now...
Earlier on, we asked McFly
if they could write a song
before the end of the show,
including the words Sofa,
Administration and Hyundai.
It's time to see how they got on.
Who would like to hear the McFly's
"Sofa, Administration and Hyundai"?
Right, play it!
Here we go.
Here we go, ready?
♪ Sofa, Hyundai, Administration ♪
♪ You said we're manufactured ♪
♪ But guys, you got it wrong ♪
♪ We did this stupid challenge ♪
♪ And we wrote this song in half an hour! ♪
♪ Sofa, Hyundai ♪
♪ Administration ♪
♪ In half an hour ♪
♪ Sofa, Hyundai ♪
♪ Administration ♪
♪ Our reputation to lose ♪
♪ It's why we wrote the Top Gear Blues ♪
♪ Jeremy's antique ♪
♪ The hamster just squeaks ♪
♪ James is such a geek and
I really wanna know who The Stig is ♪
♪ Sofa, Hyundai ♪
♪ Administration ♪
♪ Who is The Stig? ♪
♪ Sofa, Hyundai ♪
♪ Administration ♪
♪ Our reputation to lose ♪
♪ When I sing the Top Gear Blues ♪
Solo! One, two, three!
One, two, three, four!
♪ Jeremy's antique ♪
♪ The hamster just squeaks ♪
♪ James is such a geek and
I really wanna know, who's The Stig? ♪
♪ Sofa, Hyundai ♪
♪ Administration ♪
♪ Yeah, who is The Stig? ♪
♪ Sofa, Hyundai ♪
♪ Administration ♪
♪ Our reputation to lose, that's why
we wrote the Top Gear Blues ♪
♪ My penis grows huge
when I sing the Top Gear Blues ♪
♪ I'm a little confused ♪
♪ That's why we sing... ♪
♪ the Top Gear... ♪
♪ Blues ♪
All right!
- Thank you.
- Thanks.
That was brilliant, and
now we're going to do
something that almost certainly...
won't be.
Yeah, because we're going
to play us out right now.
I'm on bass.
The last time I played one
of these, I broke it... on the singer,
and that was about 20 years ago,
so I might be a bit rusty.
Yeah, and I have to say,
my piano that I've got at home
doesn't have all these switches
and knobs on it, and I normally use it
to play things like Bach and Beethoven,
but Jeremy wants us to do
something by a Billy Ocean.
Yes.
I decided we're going to do
"Red Light Spells Danger", because
I listened to it, and apart from a couple
of twiddly bits I'm a bit nervous about,
I reckon it's okay for someone
who's only had seven lessons.
How hard can it be?
Don't say that, please!
Anyway, we do need a lead singer.
Please welcome, ladies
and gentlemen, Justin Hawkins!
This is going to be beautiful.
- Yeah!
♪ Red light spells danger ♪
♪ Can't hold out much longer ♪
[CROWD LAUGHS]
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
What was that?
I dropped my sticks.
[CROWD LAUGHS]
Your hands sometimes
crash into each other...
Well, if you didn't have so many drums...
I've got another packet here.
What? Is that why
you carry them?
Getting through 20 drumsticks a day?
I've got quite a few.
Here we go!
♪ Red light spells danger ♪
♪ Can't hold out much longer ♪
♪ You took my heart and turned me on ♪
♪ And now the danger sign is on ♪
♪ I never thought the day would come ♪
♪ When I would feel alone without you ♪
♪ Can't stop running to you ♪
♪ I feel love coming through you ♪
♪ Girl, with you beside me ♪
♪ Hold on, heaven guide me ♪
♪ Red light, feel the red light ♪
♪ Oh, it's a danger warning ♪
♪ Can't hold on ♪
♪ Can't hold on much longer ♪
♪ No, no, no, no... ♪
♪ I had my fun, I played around ♪
♪ Without a love to tie me down ♪
♪ I always used to kiss and run ♪
♪ I never wanted love to catch me ♪
♪ Can't stop running to you ♪
♪ I feel love coming through you ♪
♪ Girl, with you beside me ♪
♪ Hold on, heaven guide me ♪
♪ Red light, feel the red light ♪
It's gonna be the best
Comic Relief day ever!
Let's clap your hands up in the air!
Good night, Dunstvold!
Good night, the world.
HAMMOND: Sorry.
Sorry.
CLARKSON: Sorry, everyone.
HAMMOND: Sorry, Billy Ocean.
Sorry, everybody else.