[CHEERING AND APPLAUSE]
Thank you, thank you.
Hello and welcome to what is
tonight, a Top Gear Special.
It's special because it is just one big film.
Yep, and to make it, we had to go on holiday.
Well, you say it was a holiday,
but actually it was a fly-drive holiday.
So it wasn't a holiday at all, because,
of course, you get to the car hire desk
and there's the gormless
man with the spiky hair,
and he types "War and Peace"
into his computer for 16 hours,
and then he doesn't know where England is,
and he steals your driving licence,
and then he directs you to a car park
where your car isn't.
So we were going to try and see
if we could make it any better.
Rather than suffer the misery of hiring
a car, maybe it made more sense to buy one.
We were each given a budget of $1,000.
Yes. Now, here is
the really clever bit.
At the end of our holiday, which is
essentially a road trip across four states,
we would see if, instead of simply
having to hand the hired car back,
we could sell our cars and
get most of the $1,000 back.
It was brilliant. Now, in the holiday,
we had stones thrown at us by rednecks.
We crashed into a river full of alligators.
What else happened?
We had to eat a squirrel.
Anyway, the big challenge was:
Could we buy a car for less than
it cost to rent one for a fortnight?
Let's find out!
Miami, partly sunny
84 degrees.
♪ "Sinnerman (Felix Da Housecat's Heavenly House Mix)"
Nina Simone
CLARKSON: Yes, Miami, home to
all the most successful drug dealers,
this year's Mr Big Mac,
and Silicon Valley.
All very glamorous,
but our journey began here,
in the city's used car lots.
This is where we had a morning to find
a set of wheels for less than $1,000.
♪ "Superfly"
Curtis Mayfield
I think I'd quite like to
take this one for a test drive.
MAY: What's under the bonnet of that?
- It's a V6.
- V6?
- Yes.
- Got anything with a V8?
- I wanted a muscle car, so I went straight
to a dealership that sells Corvettes.
Have you got the keys?
Thank you.
400 horsepower, a 5.7-litre V8.
OK, how much is it?
$64,815.
64...
- 815.
- Thousand dollars?
-Yeah.
What if I gave you $1,000 for it?
- $1,000?
- Mm.
Richard, it seems,
was being similarly ambitious.
♪ "Waltz"
Kem Kraft
- How much is this?
- $89,900.
I need something a bit less than that.
- A little bit less than that?
- Less than that.
- So how much for a Cougar?
- Cougars are anywhere from 35 to 200,000.
- Yeah...
- Depending upon the condition and so on.
I need something
that's a bit less than that.
A bit less than that?
- How much for a Challenger?
- Challengers start at $20,000.
- $19,900.
- Less than that.
- Less than that?
See this here?
Look, he's turning right on a red light.
That is America's only
contribution to Western civilization.
There's never been a better
time to buy a Johnson...
♪ "Trainspotting"
Primal Scream
MAY: I was the only one using
even a modicum of common sense.
Would you take $1,000 for this?
- OK, now, that's going
to be a little bit difficult.
♪ "N 2 Gether Now (DJ Premier Instrumental)"
Limp Bizkit
CLARKSON: Soon I took a leaf out
of James's book, lowered my sights
and quickly found a tidy Camaro
at a place called Adolf's.
$2,900, this. It's a big ask
to get him down to $1,000.
Might offer him a burger.
Very popular with murderers, these cars.
- Yeah.
♪ "What's My Line-Up?"
Graeme Revell
HAMMOND: Meanwhile, I'd found
something we don't have in Britain,
a dealership specializing
in ex-government cars.
This will have been a police car,
you can tell by the color,
the hole for the aerial,
and it says "Police Interceptor" on it.
Now, this one was
probably, I don't know,
maybe a spy because
there's no badging on that.
That could have been a Men in Black
and that was a Batman.
Basically, the important thing is
they've all been properly maintained
and I'm told they're dirt cheap.
And indeed they were, but even
these were beyond my budget.
- I don't have anything right now for $1,000.
- Even sensible James was struggling.
- I want a real Kojak, smoking...
- Ah, a real cool car, huh?
- Yeah.
- How about a '99 Honda Civic?
CLARKSON: Meanwhile, back at Adolf's,
negotiations on the Camaro
had broken down.
♪ "Boundaries"
Rhian Sheehan
Well, it's not going well, mate.
- I thought that we'd
get here and we'd find
sort of fantastic old American
'80s cars for 300 dollars.
- I did, I did. I thought we'd just be tripping
over Oldsmobile Cutlasses and Firebirds.
- Yeah.
- It's cause we're buying in that '90s period
when they were just making rubbish.
I mean, I'm looking at a Buick Le Sabre.
- God, don't.
- It was rubbish when it was
new, it was built by idiots
and it's rubbish now. I've got...
You know, we've got one hour left.
Shit, have we?
And I've reached the
bottom end of the town.
Yeah, I wouldn't have the Chinese
food around here, let's put it that way.
♪ "We're No Here"
Mogwai
CLARKSON: The fact was, though,
if we were going to find cars for $1,000,
we'd have to go to an even
lower bottom end of the town.
How much murdering happens here?
- A lot. If you go one mile away
here, if you go to any street...
- I'll be murdered.
- Yeah.
Everybody here, they have guns.
Including me.
Wanna see?
- He's not joking!
- That's real, here.
.25.
- Now you see, I wasn't ready for that.
Welcome to the United States.
- This is his other gun.
That's not a shotgun,
Robert, that's a rifle.
Right, it's a rifle. This shotgun is
somewhere else, I don't know where it is.
And you need this if you're
going to be a car salesman.
The guy right here, if you go two
blocks down here, he got shot five times.
- Why, by someone buying a car?
- But he killed the guy.
- He killed him?
He killed the guy, finally.
- So why have you got
telescopic sights on it?
Because if they go far
away, you just shoot them.
You saw the movie John Wayne, the
guy is running all the way, like 500 feet.
And you shoot him right there.
- Hammond.
Yes, Jeremy, how you doing?
Just been told by my new
best friend, Robert the Persian,
if you go beyond 79th Street,
you will definitely be murdered.
Shot.
Goodbye.
Hammond is wearing cowboy boots.
They're going to shoot him, aren't they?
Is it south or north of 79th Street?
I can't go.
♪ "Chan Chan"
Buena Vista Social Club
I decided the best plan was
to stay on 79th Street itself,
and came across what must be
the most optimistic dealer in town.
Oh, well, needs must.
♪ "Mercado Nuevo"
John Murphy
CLARKSON: The lesson
we'd learned already
was that it was easier
to rent a car than buy one,
but we weren't giving up.
Believe me, I'm desperate now.
I'm desperate for wheels.
Distressed look on the roof, gunshot holes.
So the car's got a history.
It's massive. Oh, no.
It's got a tree growing out of it.
There's been an accident over
there, but the car's still running,
and I was just wondering if I
could make her an offer for it.
We've been ambitious here, I think.
This $1,000 is a low amount of money.
I therefore decided to go
beyond the lower back end of town.
You guys got any ideas where
I can find a car for $1,000?
- $1,000?
- Oh, god, you've got some great teeth!
Have you seen these teeth?!
- You want it today?
- It's got to be today.
OK. All right, let me get back to you.
- Go right here to the stop sign.
- Yeah.
Hook a right,
go up exactly two blocks.
- Oh, what, this way?
- Yeah.
Amazingly, the tip paid off,
and I was the first to arrive at
our prearranged meeting point.
The Miami Jai-Alai Stadium.
♪ "Parade of the Charioteers"
City of Prague Philharmonic
This is a Chevrolet Camaro, the RS model.
♪ "Evil Rabbit"
Roots Manuva
Five-liter V8 engine, five-speed
gearbox, rear-wheel drive.
A full-on American muscle car.
Only three previous murderers,
and I only paid $800 for it.
I am... It's a brilliant,
brilliant, brilliant find.
Then Hammond turned up.
♪ "The High Chaparral"
City of Prague Philharmonic
Oh, dear. He's never
been to America before,
and now he's bought himself
what he thinks all Americans have.
That is bluff!
What do you think?
- I knew... Well.
- It's a Dodge Ram.
It's terrible!
A dent?
No, there's a few dents
and bits missing, but it's basic.
It's basic motoring
at its very best.
- You know how a Mercedes goes?
- Yeah.
It's not a Mercedes. It's not a Mercedes.
♪ "Brief Description"
Tom Verlaine
- How much?
- $1,000.
That shuts.
- $1,000?
- Yes.
- $800. I'm already $200 ahead of you.
- $800?
- The RS model.
- Was that the basic one?
Of course it wasn't the basic one.
RS is "Rally Sport".
I'd ask James on that one when he
arrives, but I'm not entirely sure it was.
It was the RS, the IROC Z...
The RS was the...
- Yes.
- Yeah, and the Q was the...
I'll keep quiet about that one.
But no, every single
thing on it works...
nearly.
- Oh, it's a manual.
- Yeah, five on the floor, rear-wheel drive.
I've got a muscle car.
How many horsepower?
200 and a bit.
- Rubbish.
- 170.
190.
How do they get such a small
amount of horsepower from a car?
The more pressing question,
though, was, "Where was James?"
He will have walked
into a dealership, "Hello",
and they'll have shot him.
How can he take so long?
- Because that's what he does.
- I mean, he'd be lost.
♪ "Pusherman"
Curtis Mayfield
- Good grief, I thought that was a train!
- That's...
- Titanic!
- That's a Cadillac!
- No, wait.
I've changed my mind.
It's an aircraft carrier.
- That's really big.
That, gentleman, is how you do it.
It's a 1989 Cadillac Brougham sedan.
- What do you think?
- Well, this is terrible.
It's like a long walk round it.
It's a really long walk.
- I like that, though.
- It doesn't just move up and down, look.
It goes straight from side to side.
- Have you seen the roads around here?
That is a perfect car
for the environment. $900!
♪ "Vanishing Dub"
Primal Scream
HAMMOND: And you can see why.
- It's out of repair.
- Don't do that.
- No, it's got newspaper in it.
- You can date it.
- I know when it was repaired.
- It was a Wednesday.
- What size engine is this thing?
- Five litre V8.
- It's not fast, but it is fabulous.
- You don't say!
Is it not, mate? I took one look and
thought, "Oh, it's like a Lotus Exige."
HAMMOND: James then turned on our cars.
- The wheels are odd.
- No, I've got an alloy.
♪ "Out of the Blue (Into the Fire)"
The The
That's my alloy. Check out my alloy.
This has just been made out of bits.
It hasn't!
- Ah!
- It smells of bodies.
- Oh, it does smell a bit ripe.
- Hold on.
That's the clothes of
the last person they killed!
It is!
Oh, my!
Oh, God, no!
That's the last person the driver killed!
Don't...
The poor man was trying to get out.
- James and I have bought cars.
- Yes.
You've bought a pick-up truck.
Now, the reason yours is in better condition
is because it's just a pick-up truck.
- It's lovely. I'm delighted.
- I quite like the pick-up truck.
- Oh, come on! What, compared to the Camaro?
- This is the land of the pick-up truck.
- You don't like the Camaro?
- I'm sorry. I don't.
Well, I do. I mean, one of those
in good nick? Yes.
Yours is a dog.
- It isn't.
- It is... Jeremy!
But every one of us
has got something better
than you get from a
rental desk at an airport.
BOTH: Oh, yeah.
CLARKSON: To find out how good
our cars were, we were told
to head to a racetrack
90 miles north of Miami.
There we'd be given a series of challenges.
♪ "Life is a Highway"
Rascal Flatts
I'm in a murderer's muscle
car heading through Miami.
Yes!
This is brilliant! I love pick-up trucks!
It's... a Cadillac.
I'm absolutely staggered!
I've even got a functioning radio.
Although there's only one station
it'll pick up, which is Gospel.
Ready?
My God is the
temple of the Holy Spirit.
Yes!
- Jesus Christ is my Lord. My savior...
-Yes, I agree with you.
Temperatures are a big deal.
We're well into the 90s, maybe 100.
♪ "American Dream (Afterlife Remix)"
Jakatta
The mono radio station,
however, was the tip of an iceberg.
If I'm honest, there are one
or two issues with my Camaro.
The rev counter, for example, broken.
Then there's an alarming knocking
noise from the front suspension
when you go over a bump
or when you're on full lock.
The others, too, were finding problems.
Now we're alone here
as I can admit to one or two
very small faults with my Cadillac.
The first is that squeak, which is a
loose belt or bearing or something.
The other, it is
fantastically slow, this thing.
I'm doing 55 and I'm
putting my foot down
and I'm really struggling
to get it up to 60.
If I'm honest, it does
pull a little bit to the right.
And if I brake, it pulls
to the left really badly.
I'm right behind Richard Hammond's
Dodge Ram and I've just noticed
for the first time
that the body doesn't line up...
[car honks]
Hang on...
with the wheels quite right.
But the worst problem by a
mile is the air conditioning, which,
as you can probably see from
the state of my shirt, is broken.
92% humidity. No air con.
The only consolation I have is that Hammond's
air conditioning doesn't work either.
Well, the air conditioning not
working is pretty much perfect.
For the first time I've got a
radio on one of these trips.
CLARKSON: But enough
of the car's little foibles.
It was time to settle down and enjoy
our journey across the Sunshine State.
♪ "Everybody's Talkin'"
Harry Nilsson
God, Florida's awful.
Nasty insects.
Old people, fat people.
A lot of people who all offer you cheese.
"You want cheese with that?"
And then shoot you.
While Hammond roasted,
James remained smug and cool.
It's getting a bit parky actually.
I think I'll just turn the
temperature up very slightly.
Look, I'm Burt Reynolds. I'm the bandit.
Eventually we turned off the highway,
♪ "The Search for Jim"
John Murphy
and arrived at the racetrack.
The Moroso Motorsports
Park is unusual in America
because it has left-handed turns
and some which go right as well.
Perhaps that's why it was deserted,
too complicated for the colonials.
Or maybe everyone had been murdered.
Whatever, it was time
for our first challenge.
It says here that each of our cars
must complete one lap of the track.
The target is one minute, ten seconds.
Get points for every
second under that time
and you lose points
for every second over it.
But the thing is none of us
have ever seen that track.
Yes, that's going to be tricky.
- We're not driving.
- Well, who is?
Some say that he's a CIA experiment that
went wrong and that he only eats cheese.
All we know is he's not the Stig,
but he is the Stig's American cousin.
♪ "Superman March (Alternate)"
John Williams
Big Stig!
First, he squeezed himself into my Camaro.
One,
two,
three,
go!
I was expecting...
[imitates tire screeches]
♪ "Bandera"
Control Machete
0-60 in 7.9 seconds.
- Yeah, once.
- It can do 110 and he's doing that now.
- No more.
- It's limited. It's electronically limited.
- No, it's just naturally limited
to 110 because it's rubbish.
Lean that weight in there, Big Stig!
There he goes! One minute,
nine seconds on our top stopwatch.
- Is that good?
- We don't know, do we?
CLARKSON: What we did know
was that the Pimpmobile was next.
I'm going to need a calendar
for this, not a stopwatch.
Have you got a diary?
I'm going to hold this stone
and as it's eroded by the wind,
that'll give us an idea
of how long he's been.
Aircon Max.
Oh, cock.
- It's broken, isn't it, mate?
- It's run out of electricity.
CLARKSON: To raise the Titanic,
we borrowed a battery booster.
Is that for starting your
watch when it stops?
That's just... Oh, it's begun.
One,
two,
three,
go!
♪ "Wichita Lineman"
Glen Campbell
It's moved off!
It's still moving off!
24 days.
I'm getting older.
It looks fabulous!
- C'mon, admit it looks good!
- We've got plenty of time to admire it.
The Cadillac certainly seemed to
suit Big Stig's relaxed driving style.
Look at that. On the grass.
But would the match made in heaven
be able to beat the Camaro's 1:09?
- Yay!
- Go on.
1:14.
So now it was all down
to Hammond's hillbilly mobile.
- Three. Go!
- Let it rip! Yeah!
Oh, nice!
- Is that manual?
- Sounds very... Yeah!
Stick shift.
Four on the floor with overdrive.
♪ "Runnin' Down A Dream"
Tom Petty
CLARKSON: Actually,
it all looked pretty promising.
If this beats mine,
I'm going to have to kill you.
And I am in a Camaro,
so don't think that won't happen.
Oh, it's a proud and noble thing.
You've seen Brokeback Mountain
and thought, "I want a piece of that life.
"Not that piece. I'll have the pick-up truck."
Although the truck had started well,
in the last few
tight corners it was rubbish.
Have you seen how my
alloy glints in the sun?
- What were you, 1:14?
- Yeah.
- 12, 13...
- No, it can't...
- 1:14...
- No!
Yes!
How could that happen?
1:16.9!
I think that's more to do with
the Stig being too big to get...
It didn't make the turn!
Fat Stig's work was done.
♪ "The Search for Jim"
John Murphy
And so it was time for the next challenge.
"You must each accelerate
your car to 50 miles an hour.
"When you reach 50 miles an hour,
you must brake as hard as you can."
So this is a test of acceleration
and braking altogether?
Yes, "you must brake
before the end of the track.
"At the end of the track, there is a river...
There's no big deal.
"...full of alligators".
And that wasn't a misprint.
I should explain, that is the track.
So if you look up there, OK, there it is.
OK, and here, this is alligator infested.
There's another one.
We drew hot dogs and mine was the shortest.
I hope he doesn't die at the end.
It's saltwater crocodiles you
need to worry about, I think.
Oh no, I hope he doesn't go
in the river, that would be awful.
Here we go!
♪ "Helicopter Delivery"
Graeme Revell
The hell with the clutch!
The spirit had started.
Come on, 30, I don't want
to be eaten by an alligator.
35, 40, 45, it's 50!
That's doubly disappointing.
Number one, he's not dead.
Yep.
And number two,
the fastest accelerating car here
only just stopped before the grass.
Surely though, the huggy bear mobile would
struggle to do 0-50-0 in the distance.
♪ "Precinct Breach"
Graeme Revell
Whoa!
That is movement.
Oh, come on, car!
Come on, come on,
come on, I'm nearly there!
Brake!
Strewth! That had me worried.
I should imagine he's clenched in there.
Eight tons of Caddy.
♪ "Coliseum Finale"
Sean Callery
I was really nervous.
I'd just seen Big Stig try to
stop my truck and fail completely.
No way, it's 20.
Here he comes to a certain death.
40, 45, it takes ages.
Oh my God.
Oh no!
That is quite funny.
Hammond!
Are you alive?
Alligators, mate.
Yeah.
Shall I suggest we may
have made them angry?
I've just driven in their-
into their living room.
Such an unsufferable oaf.
Oh, there's my pick-up, look.
The cars had survived
their ordeal by track just...
But the next morning, the real test began.
A sweltering 800-mile
road trip to New Orleans.
♪ "Six Feet Under (Rae & Christian Remix)"
Thomas Newman
- Today, partly cloudy, highs in the
lower 90s, chance of thunderstorms 30%.
Things started badly.
[Engine starts]
HAMMOND: Has it got petrol in it?
CLARKSON: Yeah, look, it's full.
- Well, yeah, but has it got petrol in it?
It could be broken.
When did you last put petrol in it?
- Miami.
Now you come to mention it.
- Stupid man!
It's a five-litre V8.
Sit down.
- The car is fine. What's happened is...
- Mine's run out of electricity again.
- You're joking.
- Can I borrow your van and the jump leads?
- See how prepared we are on this show.
- You had the leads in your car?
- No, no, you had the leads.
- I'm not a stupid man.
HAMMOND: I've got a door panel,
some bolts, and that's it.
- What's the matter?
MAY: He's lost the jump leads.
- He's lost the jump leads.
- He's lost the jump leads! He has lost...
This isn't going well, is it?
If you're thinking of coming
to America, this is what it's like.
You've got your Comfort Inn,
you've got your Best Western
you've got your Red Lobster where you eat.
Everybody's very fat, everybody's
very stupid, and everybody's very rude.
It's not the Holiday
programme, it's the truth.
Eventually, the leads were found,
and Hammond positioned
himself for the jump start.
MAY: No, it's not funny!
[laughter]
CLARKSON: We're off!
♪ "Kowalski (Automator Mix)"
Primal Scream
I'm sweating already.
- Yes, I'm not going to be for much longer.
- It's not a sunny day, it's
just a humid day today.
Do you know what this is?
Tropical.
No, that's the approach of a cold front.
That's tall human limbs for the height.
[THEY LAUGH]
It's bigger than you expect.
You don't feel like...
I'd love to know what
Hammond thinks he looks like.
Chewing gum, his aviators, his
cowboy hat and his pick-up truck.
MAY: To help relieve
the tedium of the journey,
the production office had
provided us with CB radios,
and for those we needed
appropriate call signs.
Brokeback, Brokeback. This is Murderer.
This is Brokeback,
to Murderer and The Captain.
[Incomprehensible chatter]
I wonder why these CB radios
never caught on.
Braker, breaker,
one-nine, contact, eyeball
10-10 till we do it again, Captain Slow.
[Incomprehensible chatter]
He's there and I can't understand it.
♪ "The Drive to Ripley's"
David Holmes
This was hopeless, so we changed channels.
Hello, I'm 22. Are you there?
- Yo, big boy!
And finally made contact with a native.
[Radio chatter]
That's him in that truck!
He's asking...
He's asking another lorry driver where he
might find a lady friend for the afternoon.
[Radio chatter]
All they've got to talk about on that CB
is the weather and prostitutes.
"It's raining, I'm going north
and I'm looking for a hooer".
CLARKSON: As we headed northwest,
the heat and humidity became unbearable.
♪ "First Name Unknown"
Primal Scream
You're sitting there in the winter,
you can't imagine what it's like
to be in an un-air-conditioned
car in Florida now.
It's so hot.
Danger persists in the hot west.
Even though almost a quarter
of the fire is contained,
much of it is still burning out of control.
CLARKSON: Only the
insufferable May wasn't suffering.
Chaps, it's May here, just to
let you know that my air conditioning
is working very nicely
at 65 degrees Fahrenheit.
Yes, all right!
CLARKSON: But then,
the smile was wiped from his face...
again.
♪ "JU-87"
Primal Scream
I brought you some presents.
I've got you a steak and cheese biscuit.
- What?
- And I've brought you a fan.
- Really?
- Yeah. We've got fans.
- That's fantastic, mate!
- How do you feel now?
Yeah, air-con, there it is!
[THEY LAUGH]
See what I've got?
Ham and cheese, yes.
"Dundee, ham and cheese",
I'll read you the ingredients.
Blah, blah, blah, blah...
and "Imitation American cheese".
- So it's the only thing that hasn't
actually got any cheese on it.
- Yes.
After our Imitation American lunch, it
was my turn to help the stricken Cadillac.
Oh, yes!
Oh, I'm back in the sweatbox.
♪ "Woke Up This Morning"
A3
Excessive heat
warnings continuing.
Now, what that is doing is just
turbocharging warm air into my face.
Nice one.
Jeremy, this is Brokeback.
Did you cut the wire?
You want your man to look good,
but words like exfoliant scare him?
CLARKSON: The miles passed,
with the Cadillac endlessly breaking down.
No!
- Have you got the leads?
- No, you've got the leads.
Offers to qualified buyers
on select models.
CLARKSON: Still, thanks to
the automatic windscreen washes
at Florida service stations...
No, no!
...Hammond and I could at least enjoy some refreshing showers
while he got it going again.
The Cadillac, however, was
not the only trouble-maker.
After just 200 miles, my Camaro
was hardly tip-top either.
♪ "The Great Drive By"
Funki Porcini
Right, sit-rep on the Camaro.
Some of the headlights are working,
the dashboard has come off,
all the dials are broken,
one radio speaker remains,
however, and it's good!
The good news is that with God's help,
we can stop global warming.
In a world where
tails stop wagging,
sticks don't get fetched,
and chew toys stay dry,
one man dares to step
forward and declare...
I can get to the root of
your dog's depression.
♪ "The Great Drive By"
Funki Porcini
Eventually, our Top Gear fly-drive
holiday convoy reached the 300-mile mark.
And as a reward, the production
office gave each of us $100
to buy an accessory that might in
some way make our journey less arduous.
♪ "We're Out of Here"
Funki Porcini
Hoping and praying that James
had bought a new battery for
his stupid Cadillac, we all
met up to show off our new toys.
- A trailer?
- No, a Freedom Grill 500.
- A grilling system?
- It's a grilling system.
- What is it?
[CLARKSON LAUGHS]
I have been...
- No!
- No way!
Look at that!
Drop tailgate, cooking platform,
what do you think?
Gordon Ramsay hasn't got
anything like that in his kitchen.
Have you got anything that good, James?
- No.
Right, I got...
a clothes rack.
- What?
- Look at my perfectly pressed linen jacket.
- He has a linen jacket on a clothes rack.
- Don't wobble it.
OK, so you step into your car,
and here, if you look, is a shower.
- In your car?
- Yep.
- But where do you get the water from, then?
- It comes from the cool box
in the back, this tube.
And then you just plug this
into the cigarette lighter,
hit that button, refreshing shower.
I bet you're jealous.
♪ "Yellow Rose"
A3
Sadly, though, our dreams
of luxury living were shattered
when we received
the next challenge.
"Tonight, you will be camping."
- What?
- I know.
"And you are only allowed to eat what
you find dead at the side of the road."
What, you mean roadkill?
Yeah, you're only allowed...
It's on the... yes.
So it's animals that we find
by the side of the road dead?
Yeah, that's our supper.
Hey, just think about it.
You can prepare the food,
like for cooking, wash it.
I can then cook it.
James can dress for dinner.
♪ "JU-87"
Primal Scream
- Potatoes, tomatoes, it's a lot to know.
- I can see that.
So let me ask you, how high should
a pineapple bounce when it's ripe?
OK, sit-rep.
The power steering pump
really is on its last legs.
I've got a terrible wheel wobble.
But I'm cool for the
first time since I set off.
I am cool now.
♪ "Constantine End Titles"
Brian Tyler, Klaus Badelt
To increase our chances
of finding some roadkill,
we swapped the
interstate for smaller roads.
And very quickly, we got lucky.
What on the right? What's that?
Do you know what?
I don't fancy it.
CLARKSON: No matter, though,
because further down the road
I came across a
fresh and tasty possum.
But then...
James, don't run over it, you...
You blithering idiot, you just run over it!
That's not edible now, is it?
♪ "Bessie"
Randy Newman
For flattening our supper,
James was punished.
Eventually, we did find fresh
meat, but it was a bit too fresh.
HAMMOND: I thought
you were going to run it over.
- No, even I wouldn't do that!
Don't do that, tortoise!
How can you have wild...
There's no wild tortoises.
- Well, they've got to be somewhere.
- It's escaped from
some eight-year-old girl.
- How does a tortoise escape?
Come back, come back!
♪ "A Real Indication"
Thought Gang
Finally, though,
ten miles down the road...
We've got dinner!
- Squirrel.
- Check that out!
I think that with a bit of
cheese will be delicious.
Look at May's face!
I never told you about
my vegetarianism, did I?
♪ "Hands of Time"
Groove Armada
CLARKSON: Soon,
we were near the field
where we would be
camping for the night.
Right now, the sun's going down,
I'm with my mates,
it's down below 90 degrees.
We're in the Deep South.
It's a pleasant evening.
This is nice.
♪ "Laurens Walking"
Angelo Badalamenti
But we still only had a squirrel for
dinner, so I peeled off for one last forage
while the others went ahead to set up camp.
HAMMOND: Sorry.
Right, we've got work to do.
I'm thinking squirrel on the rack,
and then maybe, here's my plan,
with a few herbs garnished,
something like that.
I'm thinking if I cook it once,
and then maybe cook it again,
so it'll go like crispy duck,
only it's a squirrel.
Is he ever coming back?
We can't just lob it on, can we?
OK, well, with a rabbit, you take the
head off, you go down the middle...
But all we've got to
do it with is a tent peg.
Didn't you bring a penknife?
Time passed, and still no sign of Jeremy.
I'm not peeling it, mate.
I don't see why I should do it.
- Come on.
- I don't want to peel a squirrel.
I'm going to bring it over to you.
- Is that a car?
- Is it Jezza?
James?
- What's he got?
- In all seriousness,
that's...
What?!
You have got to be...!
♪ "Lawrence of Arabia: Overture"
City of Prague Philharmonic
It's a flaming cow, mate!
Main course.
Yeah?
I'm thinking how long I've been
in the sun putting that tent up.
- Why?
- Because what I'm seeing...
[HAMMOND LAUGHS] You'll love this...
is a cow on the roof of your Camaro.
- It is, isn't it? There is a cow on there.
- It is!
Now, I don't want to be
pedantic, but is it roadkill?
What, are you suggesting I ran it down?
- Well...
- Check out the front of my car.
I had to find someone to help me
get it on there, but I didn't run it down.
It was at the side of the road,
now it's on the roof and it's our supper!
Do you know what to do with it?
We'll, we've got to...
Peel it.
I'm not peeling that!
MAY: First, though,
we had to get it off the roof.
What if I go round a corner
quite quickly, backwards?
- Um, left hand down, yeah.
- If I reverse... left hand down,
it'll roll over that way, do we think?
I reckon she's good to go.
Yes, there you go!
- Hey, Jeremy!
- What?
I'm better, I can't see a cow
on the roof of your Camaro anymore!
- I'm not hungry.
- What?
I'm not hungry.
You!
It stinks, Jeremy.
♪ "Brokeback Mountain Pt. 3"
Gustavo Santaolalla
That night, Brokeback and I feasted
on beef and squirrel
and then, with May in bed, we decided
it would be better for all of us
if the air conditioning
in his car were to break.
♪ "Middlesex Times"
Michael Andrews
- Shhh!
- Okay.
[WHISPERS] Sorry!
Why don't we just hit it with a hammer?
[HAMMOND LAUGHS]
Oh, hang on!
Hang on, hang on!
[THEY LAUGH]
They really built
these old buses, it's ridiculous!
[CLARKSON LAUGHS]
I'm just hitting it with a spatula.
Another mosquito just bit my face.
It's not working.
[CLARKSON LAUGHS]
He's going to notice, isn't he?
[BOTH LAUGH]
♪ "Rain Hammers"
Thomas Newman
Another humid day dawned,
and now May knew what it felt like.
Those pathetic,
lager-swilling, barbecuing, redneck
thugs that I call my co-presenters
have vandalized my car.
I have had to make a few
modifications to the car this morning.
Because of the cow incident,
I lost the aerial,
so now I've got an iStation instead.
And that, teamed with the fan,
means I really can't see where I'm going.
Also, because some cow did get into
the car, I'm using air fresheners here
to cover up the smell,
so I can't really see where I've been.
Oh, and, um, the passenger seat.
That got a lot of cow juice on it,
so it's now in the back of Hammond's truck.
♪ "Tess"
David Holmes
By this afternoon,
skies will be considerably cloudy
with showers
and thunderstorms likely.
Northeast winds, 5-10 mph.
Come on!
Alabama's only 40 miles now!
Our scrapyard cars had covered 650 miles,
and, inevitably, they were
becoming more than just metal.
This whole thing now really
sums up why I love cars.
I mean, take this Camaro.
The dash is more plastic
than an American newsreader.
The engine's got less power than Belgium,
the suspension is softer than the
journalism in an in-flight magazine,
and of course, it reeks of cow.
But, I adore it, because...
you can just sense it wants to keep going.
And I bet James is exactly the same
there in the Cadillac.
I bet he's having exactly the same emotions.
I'd rather be in this now
than an Enzo, and I'm not joking.
HAMMOND: But before we entered Alabama,
we had to go to Bagdad
for our next challenge.
♪ "Ashes to Ashes"
Hans Zimmer
This is it!
We are in Bagdad.
Not a place I was expecting
to visit on this trip.
Challenge time.
Lose five pounds in one hour?
Yep, sweat it away! Come on then.
No.
OK, it says here
we must not be shot or arrested
as we drive across
the proud state of Alabama.
But we will get bonus points if we can
get one of the others shot or arrested.
I don't understand, how do we do that?
You will therefore decorate
one another's cars in such a way
to draw maximum attention to yourself
in this Bible-bashing, redneck,
deeply Christian part of the Union.
Decorate?
I think what it means is we each have
to write slogans on the other cars.
- So you...
- To get them killed?
- Yeah.
- All right!
So, you do Hammond's,
take it away into the bushes.
- You do...
- I'm doing yours. I'm getting you killed.
- Well, come on!
- I've got another idea...
♪ "Loop Garoo"
Dr. John
The South, The South...
It's, it's Christian, short hair,
they don't like communists...
What is closest to their heart?
I've got to get him killed, this is
a once in a lifetime opportunity.
I'd be letting you down,
me down, everybody down.
[MAY LAUGHS]
Revenge for all those height gags.
Every time he's called me Hamster.
This is for every time
you've been late and lost.
Can you tell what it says yet?
♪ "The Drive to Ripley's"
David Holmes
James, I hate you for that.
I really hate you for that.
Well, just think about all the times
you drove into the back of my Cadillac.
- Yeah.
- Do you know, actually, I think...
Honestly, we've all done a good job here,
but I do believe that the
person most likely to be shot
is indeed Hammond.
I think what you've done there,
James, is killed your friend.
Yeah.
♪ "1492, Conquest of Paradise"
City of Prague Philharmonic
CLARKSON: Gingerly,
we rejoined the open road.
Three religions down here.
George Bush,
God, country and western.
In that order.
Ascending order.
I'll be honest,
I have felt less conspicuous than this.
Here we are, sweet home Alabama.
[IMITATES GUNFIRE]
♪ "Lexington Hotel, Room 1432"
Thomas Newman
They've shot their own sign!
What are they going to do to us?
To understand what Jeremy
has actually done to my car
you have to remember
that this is deep Republican territory.
That woman is the arch-Democrat.
She is the Antichrist.
It's not just the slogan.
It's the fact that it's painted on a pick-up,
a symbol of the South. I mean...
[HORN BLARES]
Oooh!
And then, Jeremy has written
on the boot, "NASCAR sucks".
Now, that's a type of saloon car racing
that is very, very big
in this part of the world.
This is where all the drivers come from,
all the building of the cars is done,
all the supporters come from
down here, and to say it sucks,
is a bit like going up and punching
somebody's sainted mother.
No!
[Car honks]
CLARKSON: We'd survived the highway,
but then we had to pull into a town for fuel.
Oh, this is really terrifying.
Okay!
Just, um...
That's diesel.
That's... I've gone...
"Hillary for President" - that's...
that's not going down well.
This lady was cross, but not
as cross as the garage's owner.
... I'll ask you.
Now, are y'all gay, looking to see how long
it takes to get beat up in a hick town?
CLARKSON: I'm not gay, I'm married.
I've got three children.
HAMMOND: Er, no, we're not. No.
We just sort of decorated
our cars in a distinctive manner.
"NASCAR sucks",
"Country and Western is rubbish"?!
Guess what, you're in a hick town, man!
We're gonna die now, that's it.
Don't you dare! [Beep]
She said she was gonna get "the boys".
I'm gone!
So we decided to scarper.
♪ "Chant"
Hans Zimmer
I've just remembered,
I've actually got loads of petrol.
HAMMOND: And then, of all the moments...
- Oi, jump leads!
- You're joking?!
- Jump leads.
- Not now!
♪ "Your Dog Is a Dirty Pig"
Graeme Revell
This is gonna be
the quickest jump in history.
Where are they?
You get the leads, I'll start it.
Tell your friend if he
tears up my parking lot again...
The rednecks arrived.
We've just got a slight problem here.
[Beep]
This is bad!
Then, they turned on the film crews.
[Beep] Hey! If he tears...
if you tear up my parking lot...
Quick! [Engine starts]
Rocks started pelting our vans.
Five...
four, get out of here!
What's happening?
[Beep]
♪ "Precinct Breach"
Graeme Revell
For the next few moments, our TV
program became a radio show.
CLARKSON: Oh, [Bleep],
there are the pick-up trucks.
Can you get your foot down?
I think we've got a load of them on our tail.
Something's going on here,
I'm telling you.
Because these three trucks
that were in the petrol station
have now just torn past us.
HAMMOND: We need to
get these slogans off, lads.
Pull over, pull over.
♪ "Chant"
Hans Zimmer
Get the other side.
We have nothing to wipe it off with now.
CLARKSON: With the artwork
gone, we hit the road... hard.
I'm doing something I never thought I'd do,
I am running for the border.
God in heaven,
that was actually frightening.
They could have killed us!
They really do have an irony deficiency.
I honestly believe that
in certain parts of America now,
people have started
to mate with vegetables.
And then, with one problem behind us,
we ran straight into another.
♪ "Finding the Bomb"
The Dust Brothers
Oh, lightning!
Do you think this is God punishing us?
I'm just...
[Thunders]
Did you hear that?!
It was a great time to discover that the
wipers in my car were worse than useless.
This is like something
out of a horror film now.
I'm in serious trouble,
I cannot see a damn thing.
There were no exits and
stopping on the hard shoulder
in rain like this would have been suicidal,
so there was only one choice.
You're out of lane. Go right, Jeremy.
Yeah, now, this is... very bad!
- Left a bit.
Please stop raining, please stop
raining, please stop raining.
- You're out of lane, go right.
- I think I'm just going
to get out and kill myself.
Put myself out of my misery...
Oh, hell's teeth!
♪ "Celebrate the Bullet"
Selector
What with the storm
and the rock-throwing rednecks,
our fly-drive holiday
wasn't going that well.
I just wanted to get on the big British jet and go home.
I want to be met by a homosexual
in grey flannel trousers saying,
"Welcome on board,
Mr. Clarkson. Can I get you a scone?"
111 miles to New Orleans.
Come on, Camaro!
♪ "Gypsies, Tramps and Thieves"
Cher
Yes, that's it!
We're in Louisiana!
MAY: All we had to do was
get there and sell our cars.
And that, actually,
would be quite a sad moment.
I love my Cadillac.
♪ "Auto Rock"
Mogwai
I mean, we've know
each other, what, a few days
and we've had this
fantastic adventure together
all across America and it's my car now,
I know all it's foibles.
It's not the biggest truck, it's not
the fastest, it's not the best looking
but it just keeps going.
It's like a little Welsh pony.
I respect that.
This car really is like
living in an old house.
You know to kick the back door
in a certain way to make it open.
It's the same with this. I know how
to keep the power steering going.
I know how to get the best
out of what's left of the clutch.
I liked it as a kind of joke
when we started, but now...
we're like that.
♪ "Twilight of a Champion"
The The
Crossing the central
Reservation [Music]
MAY: Of course there were certain
other problems with selling our cars.
We've got some very, very bad Cadillac weave
going on on this straight stretch here.
So, I'll keep the worry beads to hand.
Whoa, relax!
We're in New Orleans and something
has come off the Camaro.
The temperature gauge is off the scale.
Come on!
MAY: Finally, though, we made it.
And my word,
were we in for a shock.
♪ "What's My Line-Up?"
Graeme Revell
We had seen on the news
what Hurricane Katrina had done
but seeing the devastation
for real was truly astonishing.
Oh, my God!
Oh, look at that!
Well now this is extraordinary.
Every house... I've been
driving now, what, 15 miles?
There isn't a pavement,
there isn't a building,
there isn't anything
that isn't smashed.
It's such a vast scale of destruction.
A year had passed
since Katrina had blown through
and we sort of assumed
that after 12 months,
the wealthiest nation
on Earth would have fixed it,
but we were wrong.
How can the rest of America
sleep at night
knowing that this is here?
It certainly gave us a problem.
The original plan had been
for us to sell our cars here
and see who could get the most money.
But in the midst of all this
that just seemed... wrong.
♪ "Vanishing Dub"
Primal Scream
We, therefore, had a conflab
and decided that we
should give our cars away.
So we called a local mission
who put us in touch with some families
who'd lost theirs in Katrina.
It's got an alloy.
It's all standard, it's not
being messed with in any way.
I mean, the guy who had this before,
it's in 150,000 miles and look,
it's like new under there.
- I like it.
- Done, it's yours!
Take the truck, it's yours.
Look after it, it's been
a good friend to me
Alright, we appreciate it.
HAMMOND: Jeremy did
his usual trick of telling it like it is.
Rev counter - not good,
speedo - not good,
fuel gauge - not good,
Dent on the roof -
that was caused by a cow,
As far as driving it is concerned,
the engine is brilliant.
♪ "Auto Rock"
Mogwai
Gearbox - tip top!
It's a good car, it's all yours.
So, although it hadn't
been the most relaxing holiday,
it had been a proper Boys' Own adventure.
And what's more, we could go home
knowing that we'd done a little bit
to help those
less fortunate than ourselves.
Well, Richard and I could,
but James sadly couldn't
even give his car away.
It's still here!
♪ "We're Out of Here"
Funki Porcini
A family came around this corner,
not ten minutes ago,
"Oh thank you, we lost
everything in Hurricane Katrina..."
And they rejected it.
Do you want a lift
to the airport in my car?
- No.
- No, me neither.
- I don't.
- I walk, thank you, ta-ra.
Hammond, can I borrow the jump leads?
No.
[CHEERING AND APPLAUSE]
Loser.
Loser, loser!
Hey.
I reckon, if you look on Google Earth,
you'll see his car, cos it'll still be there.
Well, it's not like you won't be able
to see it either. It's big enough.
Okay, so there's no doubt that
James lost that challenge
and equally no doubt that I won.
Hang on, how'd you arrive at that?
Well, my Camaro was the fastest,
it had the best brakes,
it didn't break down,
apart from the wipers... much,
so it was the best!
It wasn't actually quite as easy to give away
as you made out in that film, was it?
Well, sort of...
Why don't you tell the ladies
and gentlemen what happened
- after the cameras had been turned off?
- Yeah.
Well, a lady came and
she said she was a lawyer
representing the Christian
mission that we'd gone to,
and she said she'd been promised
by one of our researchers a '91 Camaro,
and it was a '89, and she said
that was misrepresentation
and she was going to sue me.
No, this... It really
did happen, it really did.
And then, she said
that if I gave her $20,000 in cash
she might be able
to make the case go away.
And you won't believe
what happened to us next.
No, which was that a very,
very large pick-up turned up,
full of heavily armed and very burly men,
told us to get off their street.
- Yeah!
- Yes.
So really we do have two Top Gear
top tips for you tonight.
One - yes, you can buy rather than rent,
and two - don't go to America!
Top Gear's back to its normal self
next week, so we'll see you then.
Thanks for watching. Good night!