Everyone certainly did rise to the
challenge for Sport Relief last weekend...
that we raise a total of over 20 million pounds.
Which is just...
A phenomenal amount of money.
And I'd like to take this chance to say...
Thank you for donating.
Over what was... just an incredible weekend.
Thanks, especially, to everyone
who walked, jumped, ran, hopped,
wheeled along a Sport Relief mile on Sunday.
Please, please, please, send this to your
sponsorship money as quickly as possible,
and keep donating, so we can
put your cash to some good use.
Now, as a special− Well... "treat",
another chance to see what happened
when Top Gear did a surprise makeover
on the garden of a famous sportsperson.
Who turned out, not only to
be a famous sportsperson,
but very big, really quite angry,
and not very fond of surprises.
The whole thing could have gone better.
But this is Top Gear Ground Force.
Gear.
Force.
Makeover.
Hello, and− I've just trodden in some dog poo...
Uhm...
Never mind, err... I'm sure you all remember,
the TV show, Ground Force.
The idea was that some people with regional
accents would come round to your house
while you were out,
and do up your garden.
Then you'd come home,
cry with unbridled joy, and...
then everyone would
have some warm Pomagne.
Now, sadly, it isn't on anymore,
so we thought it'd be a
good idea to bring it back.
I mean...
Gardening.
How hard can it be?
Well, I should imagine, very hard.
Well, we're going to find out.
This is the team.
There's Handy Hammond,
James "E. Dimmock" May.
And then, we've got some Poles,
who'll actually do all the work−but,
anyway, let's get cracking!
The lucky recipient of our
Top Ground Gear Force garden makeover...
is a sporting legend.
Five times Olympic gold
medalist, Sir Steve Redgrave.
A man whose shoulders
are thicker than my torso.
Great Britain on the line!
Here we go! Great Britain!
Get the gold medal
and relief all out!
And triumph for Steve Redgrave!
Five in a row, what a hero!
This is his garden,
and this is his wife, Lady Ann.
He really doesn't know, does he?
That we are doing this?
I mean, hand on your heart.
Absolutely. No idea at all.
Because everyone on
television believes−you know,
nobody believes a word on television,
but he really, genuinely, does not know.
He has no idea.
It's fantastic. Now, the garden.
Have you got any ideas?
Anything you want?
Well, Steve likes water features.
He tried one over there around the corner.
You could try one of those.
It does trickle over the top of the pot.
- No, I might be able to...
- With a fish in the bottom.
I could improve on a trickle.
- Ah.
- I do, I like fountains. We can do that.
Other than that, I don't mind,
so long as it looks... reasonable.
No, it'll look reasonable. I just
think a few features would be good.
Yeah, well, we have our tree-house.
No, that's good. We could do
some paths to it, and stuff like that...
No, that'd be good.
Now, he's home− Sir Steve is home in...
- Well, he'd be about five 'o clock tonight.
-Five 'o clock...
So it's half past eight now...
What's the maths on that?
Nine... six, seven,
eight and a half hours...
We need to get cracking.
♪ Ground Force Theme
Black Dyke Band
Right... Now, since I'm the only
country bumpkin on the team, I'm in charge.
And since I'm also the only one
who went to art college, I've drawn the plan.
So, here's what we're going to do:
There's the house, there's the garage.
So, that's over there.
Now, Sir Steve Redgrave is a very busy man.
So when he comes home,
he likes to relax.
So, I've got a sort of family
chill out barbecue area here...
with some decking
overlooking a bed full of... flowers.
And then, there's a river of gravel,
cascading down through the garden to this,
which is one of those things
that goes around the tree.
- Where's the water feature?
There isn't one.
- Why not?
All that matters in a garden
is a water feature.
No. Sorry, all that matters
in a garden is a shed.
No. Look, there isn't a shed
or a water feature. Alright?
- Rubbish.
- A garden should
speak of the man.
- It does.
- There's nothing here
that says "Olympic Rower".
- There's a river of gravel.
- It's just annoying.
It's just− Look, you have to
walk miles to get to the seat.
That's the theme of
the garden. A river of gravel.
- It's rubbish.
- He'll come out of his house
and it'll take a whole week
to wend his way.
- He just has to walk across here, just going to walk all over there.
And this bed?
You'll do the hoeing.
I'm not doing any hoeing.
I don't even know what hoeing is.
- Well, hoeing is when...
- Anyway. We don't need a hoe.
There is only one tool
you need for gardening.
And I've got it.
- It's a hammer.
- It'll be a hammer.
It's not a hammer!
- This...
- Is that a hoe?
...is all you-
[Clarkson laughs]
No, it isn't.
No. If you want to remove a plant...
Say you... Okay, there are
no thistles at this time of year,
but imagine they are thistles.
How do you get them up?
Well, you take one
of these, which is a trowel.
- Yeah.
- And then you, uh, approach it like that,
and you... dig around it.
Lift it. And there it is.
- That took you...
- About thirty seconds.
Dirty fingernails, cricked back.
It's gardening, that's what you do.
Okay, now let me show you
how I would remove it, ok?
See these three here? Ready?
[shotgun blast]
Well, granted,
they are gone, but you can't...
- They are gone.
- You can't garden with a shotgun.
They have ceased to exist.
Observe the genius of my gardening.
I'd rather he had a hammer.
You do realize we've already wasted an hour?
♪ Hornets' Nest
Black Dyke Band
CLARKSON: Hammond sent James and I off
to get supplies at something called a "garden centre".
It was a place which seemed
to be mostly full of sheds,
and what kind of nerd
would find those interesting?
MAY: Wow!
Clarkson: I, however,
wasn't experiencing such joy.
Why does everything
have to be in Latin? Every single...
[misreads] "Hamelis...
intermedia, Palidia."
Presumably, that's Latin
for "Dead twig in some mud".
Everything is dead! Look, it's all just dead.
It's all dead, look.
Just a forest of deadness.
- What's this? Just...
- That's a rose.
Will it grow by five 'o clock this afternoon?
No, I'm afraid not.
♪ Lament of the Dandelion
Black Dyke Band
CLARKSON: In the shed zone,
James was struggling to find something...
which matched his rigorous standards.
Now, this is dangerously close to being gazebo,
which means it'll be misappropriated
look, by people on exercise bicycles.
Do you have any Gorgonzola here?
Gorgon-zee-la?
Gorgonzola.
- I'll go and check for you.
- Thanks.
I don't mean Gorgonzola, do I?
That's a cheese.
That's bougainvillea, I meant.
- Pardon?
So, what's alive that I could have?
- Do you want the color?
- There is no point in paying for daffodils...
You can just go
and nick those from a roundabout.
No, I'm looking for something
for a garden. A rower's garden.
- Right.
- I've been sent to get plants...
but I just don't know, other than Gorgonzo...
No, um, what's it called...
Gonorrhea.
- Tree ferns, um...
Have you got any syphilis?
This is heading in the right direction,
the 6x4 Apex Shed, of shiplap construction.
It's a very simple structure, it has a window...
But it's not really the shed
for a man of the stature
of five times Olympic gold medal winning,
Sir Steve Redgrave, CBE.
We want something... bigger.
CLARKSON: Finally, I
found something I recognized.
Greenhouses. [coughs]
I know what they're for.
You can use them for growing apples,
and... meat.
Eggs. Stuff like that...
Stuff that need
to be warm... go in there.
We'll get one of those.
Look at this! It's a...
[misreads] "Chlamydia...
Lawsoninia."
Or, as Richard Hammond calls it,
a mighty scotch pine.
[background chatter]
Is there a single thing
in this entire shop...?
CLARKSON: So far, we've been
on the job for two hours.
And Sir Redgrave's garden
had gone from looking like this...
to looking like this...
But no matter.
We were men on the move.
[fanfare rendition
of "Smoke on the Water"]
[murmurs] Honestly, shut it.
They'll just think she fell off it, or so.
Put it back.
[Jeremy murmurs]
Good, good, come here...
Alright...
Right.
CLARKSON: In the garden, the Poles set about building the greenhouse.
And, with his usual sense of urgency,
James started on the shed.
MAY: Oh, yes...
CLARKSON: Hammond, meanwhile...
was preparing to dig
the foundations for his rivers of gravel.
- Hammond!
- What?
You've got to wear that.
What?
- You've got to wear that.
- Why?
Because...
Health and Safety say
it'll keep you healthy and safe.
Safe from what?
Right.
Clarkson: With Hammond
protected from certain death,
I got cracking
with my water feature.
Right. I want a trench
four yards long,
one yard wide... meter.
And one meter deep.
A trench.
[signaling] Trench...
But like... Charles Bronson–He was Polish...
in "The Great Escape".
Go on, dig. Dig!
Dig.
Quantity: one. Heavy Duty Workshop Door End.
Heavy Duty Workshop Plain End.
Two Heavy Duty Workshop Window Panels.
Yes.
Two Heavy Duty Workshop Plain Panels...
CLARKSON: This was ridiculous.
James had to be reminded
that we were against the clock.
Yes, I know, but
you've spent... like half an hour.
Yeah, but if the screws are not
in the right lengths in the wrong holes...
you get up at the end of the shed
with the wrong screw left over...
and it won't be long enough, and then...
- You have to dismantle
the whole thing again.
- Just build the shed.
- I'm building the shed.
- You're not building the shed...
- This is part of building the shed...
-You're naming your tools!
♪ Hornets' Nest
Black Dyke Band
Is this your tape measure?
It might be.
[shotgun blast]
[fanfare resumes]
Good news!
In the time it's taken
James E. Dimmock to organize his tools,
and Handy Hammond to dig a six-inch hole,
the Poles have already
got the glass in the greenhouse.
And this is
my water feature. It's arrived.
And it is...
[gasps] Well, it's an exquisite piece.
It really is.
The only trouble is it comes
with the Nissan Micra of pumps.
This will only shift a gallon of water a minute.
So, what I've done is brought along this...
This is the Ferrari Enzo of pumps.
Comes from the world of quarrying.
This will shift 15,000 gallons a minute.
Now, unfortunately,
you do need a generator to run it.
But that's arriving right now on the back
of the articulated lorry over there.
Now the great thing about this pump
is that it gives me flexibility.
You can either have...
I don't know, a little tinkling, gentle dribble of water,
Or you can crank it up a bit and have...
Yeah, I've made that worse.
T-That's not gone well, has it?
No, it's fine, it's- it's, umm...
This is so I can get in... To cut...
How the hell did that happen with my hi-vi on?
What you've just done is prove...
that all the Health and Safety executives'
advice is pointless, meddling twaddle.
- This is...
- If I'm honest, it didn't help.
At no point did the vest save...
That's kind of...
Oh, come on. Just push it up.
- You won't be able to.
- You will.
- You won't. It weighs...
Who ever made a lightweight digger?
- If they were light...
- James, give it a push.
If they were light, they'd fall over.
[Hammond groans]
It's heavier than I thought.
- It is. Exactly.
- It turned out to be quite heavy, yes.
It's much heavier than I thought.
We're gonna need a bigger digger.
♪ Thorny Croft
Black Dyke Band
CLARKSON: Hammond went
and got a bigger digger,
which proceeded to turn this little piece of Marlow
into the Somme.
I mean, it will grow back.
As a... gardener, I-I can tell you that.
It's grass... it grows back.
MAY: Look at that.
- Hammond, you are ruining the lawn.
The lawn is being ruined.
Where does it say
on your plans: "Big digger marks".
I've got to turn the digger round
to pull the other digger up.
CLARKSON: Over the next
half hour, all he managed to do...
was lacerate the lawn even more.
He doesn't strike me as a...
"lawn" type of bloke, Sir Steve Redgrave.
MAY: What, do you think
he prefers tractor marks and mud?
I don't think he'd be that fussed.
CLARKSON: But then,
the digger fiasco was interrupted...
by the arrival of my concrete.
♪ Thistle Dance
Black Dyke Band
The smell of civilization arriving...
CLARKSON: My genius plan
was to concrete over the lawn.
Where on my plans does it say "concrete"?
Concrete is better than grass.
Sir Steve Redgrave is a busy man.
He has no time
to mow his lawn every 20 minutes.
With this, you just
have to hoover it in the autumn.
But it looks...
Shit.
It doesn't! Grass looks shit...
because it fills up with watercress.
And, and... and lawns give me hay fever.
But you don't live here.
Well, maybe they give
Sir Steve Redgrave hay fever.
For god's sake...
Does Steve Redgrave get hay fever?
No.
Do you get hay fever?
Does any member of
Sir Steve Redgrave's family get hay fever?
No.
Wait, wait, wait...
MAY: While those two
were bickering over the lawn...
my shed was taking shape nicely.
[hammering]
So you gotta remember
is that everything good in the world...
especially everything good
that ever came out of Britain,
came out of a shed.
Radio, television, the jet engine,
printing press...
And in other countries...
The aeroplane, the hot air balloon...
See, the thing about this shelf...
[mechanical noise]
is that, on it, one day will rest a component...
that Sir Steven Redgrave CBE,
five times Olympic gold medalist,
will pick up and use
to create something brilliant.
And that can only happen
because people have sheds...
with stuff in them.
Do you see what I mean?
CLARKSON: My hay fever
removal system had hit a snag.
I ordered 20 tonnes of concrete,
which I thought would be enough...
to do the whole lawn.
In fact, it's only gonna be able
to do an area "this" big.
Which means that
this is all still gonna be grass.
And look what Hammond has done.
There isn't enough concrete
to cover this bit of lawn.
Do you think Sir Steve Redgrave
is gonna be particularly...
upset that we haven't
been able to concrete the bit of lawn...
that we've driven over
with a massive digger, which is worse?!
HAMMOND: We decided to worry
about the digger issue later,
because, on the other side of the garden,
the ever efficient Poles
had finished my tree seat.
It goes around the tree,
and then you can sit any side
and just admire the view.
And this... is exactly
how you designed, is it?
Yep, it is.
So how are you gonna get it around the tree?
Um...
Yeah...
- Well... You could...
Plant a tree in the middle,
and then it would grow in place.
Yes.
Yes, you could...
if Sir Steve Redgrave wasn't
coming home for 200 years.
Y-You could lower it from the top.
Yeah, but what about...
Look at all the branches.
I can deal with those.
He is tall but that is... ambitious.
[shotgun blast]
♪ Tulip Parade
Black Dyke Band
You can't prune a tree
with a shotgun.
Yes, you can.
[shotgun blast]
This is going well.
It's not working.
- It is working.
- It's not.
Oh yes, we're gonna have
a massive bonfire with your prunings.
[shotgun blast]
CLARKSON: As I blew the tree
to pieces with my under and over hoe,
the crane that would lower
the seat into place arrived.
MAY: Mind the tree.
[glass shatters]
CLARKSON: Sorry.
HAMMOND: Oh, yeah.
One bench solution system.
MAY: Happily, Hammond's crane
didn't have tracks.
Unhappily, it weighed 14 tons.
I've got my crane stuck, is what I've done.
What you've done now
is ruined a bit more of the lawn.
HAMMOND: It's no biggie, no biggie.
Although the crane had sunk
into Sir Steve Redgrave's lawn,
luckily the arm was long enough
to reach my tree seat.
MAY: Steady...
Afoot. Afoot.
No, up!
No, you've gotta lift it!
No!
Hammond, you idiot, man!
Honestly!
[Clarkson laughs]
How can you be so useless, man?
Listen. Honestly, that's the only bit
of this project that has gone properly.
The shed was up and perfect,
and you've wrecked the shed...
and you've wrecked your stupid...
idiotically designed
- No, this is a loss. That pile of...
- It's not a loss.
It's not a loss. It isn't...
- Because it turns out that this...
- It doesn't matter.
This is no good for shooting branches off.
No, but the river of gravel
cascading majestically through the garden
- to end in the tree seat is in despoil.
- Have you any idea...
- What?
- How far we are from a river of gravel
running through your garden?
Look what it's got. It's got a river of track marks,
and a broken... stupid toy digger in a hole.
There's a few sights along the way on the river.
The crane is stuck...
And look at the holes! Look at that.
It has gone...
How long have we been here? Four hours?
Five hours? It's gone backwards.
Guys, we do need to speed up.
CLARKSON: So, in just five hours,
we dug a trench,
crashed a digger, knocked over a shed,
concreted half the lawn,
ruined the other half with caterpillar tracks,
broken a seat, shot some flowers,
and wounded one of the Poles.
But the greenhouse was looking good.
And a short while later,
James had his shed back up as well.
♪ Lament of the Dandelion
Black Dyke Band
So, if you take the big spanner off,
you can see the big spanner is missing.
Put the big spanner on,
you know it's in the right place.
If Jeremy Clarkson came in here and did that,
you'd see immediately that
is not the correct spanner for that peg.
That should be on there,
and that should be on there.
CLARKSON: With James suffering
from an industrial bounce of OCD,
I set about removing
Sir Redgrave's flower bed.
[fanfare plays]
Now, the traditional method
for removing an unwanted rockery
is, a shovel, um...
Excuse me...
Guys, can we just hold the...
Just for a second, can we hold the music?
[fanfare ends]
Thanks.
As I was saying,
shovel, crowbars, lots of elbow grease.
There is, however, another way.
What you need is some sugar,
some fertilizer, a length of wire,
some electricity, and a plunger,
like we have here.
Okay...
Fire in the Pole!
That usually clears them.
[explosion]
CLARKSON: James didn't
take the news well.
Look what you've done
to my bloody shed, man!
I had this bomb, and...
That'll buff out.
What time is this programme on?
- Is it ten o'clock?
- Yeah.
- Is it ten o'clock on BBC Two?
- Yes.
- Are we beyond the watershed?
You're a fu–
Guys...
[band plays]
What have you done?
I thought it was more set and, it...
- I went through it and I'm...
- What?
I'm stuck...
In your concrete.
Oh, for God's sake.
W-What?
You've left foot marks.
Well, it was hardly perfect
to start with, was it?
You've already ruined
the lawn with your concrete,
and now I've walked on it. I'm sorry.
It was supposed to look like lawn,
how can it look like lawn with...
It's not green! How can it look like lawn?
Please, stop the music. Can we stop?
Please.
Stop it!
[band stops]
CLARKSON:
Soon, we had Hammond free.
And, as James rebuilt his shed... again,
I began work on me rugby posts.
And, then bring it along.
'Cause you've gotta push... Yeah.
HAMMOND:
What are you doing now?
Some rugby posts.
Have you brought anything that's on my plan?
No.
And how do you even know
that Sir Steve Redgrave likes rugby?
Uh... well, I do.
Does Sir Steve Redgrave play rugby?
No.
- Do you play rugby?
- No.
Does any member of
Sir Steve Redgrave's family play rugby?
No.
Heave!
Come on! Yes!
Yes!
- Jeremy.
- What?
No member of the
Sir Steve Redgrave family plays rugby.
Well, then they'll be able to.
[loud crash]
Actually, they won't.
CLARKSON: Again, James
was very angry with me.
I think you've got something
to say to me, haven't you?
I'm surprised how heavy rugby posts are.
Something along
the lines of "I'm sorry, James.
- "I am a fully rigged, rate A1...
- Look, you two. You two...
- Ocean going pillock!"
- Sir Steve Redgrave will be here in half an hour.
We've got to speed up again.
♪ Hornets' Nest
Black Dyke Band
CLARKSON: James' shed was mended again.
The digger was camouflaged.
And best of all,
my water feature was finished.
Do you see the adjustability of it?
You can have it high, or low.
We go low,
down...
No, that's off.
Up.
There!
Or, up!
With Sir Steve Redgrave
just minutes away,
Hammond unveiled his barbecue.
I've put some thought into this, because...
For this, I've not used coals, which take
ages to light and give you salmonella.
I've used...
Jet engines.
So, we fire them up...
- Jet engines?
- Jet engines. Two of them.
I turn them on here...
CLARKSON:
But these were tiddlers,
compared to the engine that would
cook the meat on the rotisserie.
It's actually a V1, uh...
- So, I'm just gonna...
- From a doodlebug?
Yes, it's a doodlebug engine.
There we go.
It is a bit more temperamental
than coal, but when it works...
Boy, does it work.
How do you turn that, then?
It will start turning,
you have to get it up to speed.
It turns the fan around,
which then– There you go!
- Oh, that's quite good, actually.
- It's genius.
There you go, look at that!
Yeah, i-it's... it's not...
- Yeah, that's cooked.
- It needs some adjust–
Hang on, let me... just, um...
- T-There you go...
- Oh, wow!
I didn't have it set right.
That's actually better.
See? Now, that's gonna grill it properly.
You'll get some proper...
blackening of the chicken.
That's...
That's hot, actually.
Oh!
- Ah, you utter pillock!
- Wait!
- Oh, hang on.
- No!
- No, let me do it!
- No, I'm going to do it.
Sorry, I...
- Sorry! Sorry!
- Ah! You've frozen my goolies!
- I'm sorry, it went the wrong way.
- Give it to me! Give it to me!
- It went the wrong way.
- Give it to... Let me do it!
Let me do it...
[everyone coughs]
Redgrave is coming up the drive.
What?
HAMMOND: Right.
MAY: Sir Steve Redgrave
is coming up the drive.
Well, I was
just about ready.
Where do we hide?
I don't know, behind a tree?
- In my shed.
- They always hide in Ground Force.
[whispers] Why don't we
tell him his wife did this...
and then we've been called in?
- Yeah, to put it right.
- To put it right.
And we're just about to start.
- He's coming, he's coming...
- Oh, god...
How do you think he'll react?
I don't know, seriously.
He's here, he's here, he's here...
You go. James,
go on, offer him a drink...
- No, no, no, you go, you go...
- It was your idea.
What does he look like?
Where's the drink?
Have you got the drink ready?
- Good.
- Yes...
Don't hide behind me!
I can hide behind anyway.
Look happy, just look happy.
We're pleased, we're pleased about it.
We will carry this through,
everybody. Just happiness.
- I've never been so nervous in my life.
- No, I'm scared.
- I am terrified...
- I know.
He's a big bloke.
He is very, very big.
- Yeah!
- Hi.
Sir Steve Redgrave,
I am Jeremy Clarkson.
Yeah, I know who you are.
W-We've...
It's, um...
It's what?
- Sport Relief.
I know you think we're for...
It's confused...
You're confused, I would imagine,
because we're from Top Gear,
and we thought we'd come and do...
- Top Gear Ground...
- Ground Force...
- Force Garden.
- and make your garden, improve...
but we haven't quite finished.
But if we talk– I mean, the plans,
the ideas behind it are... brilliant.
Now, we can talk you
through some of the better things.
Some of the, really...
But that's one of the worst things
that you're seeing there...
but it has better points.
Uh, can we...
This was a surprise,
just not a good one at the end of it.
CLARKSON:
The Poles could sense the mood.
We, however, would not run.
We would stand together
and face the problem
of Steve's wrath united as one.
Actually, it's Hammond's fault.
Hammond put the digger on it's side,
Hammond chewed the lawn up,
Hammond set fire to your shed,
I think it's yours and Hammond's fault, frankly.
- I think he's going to...
- It was a perfectly good shed.
If he had come and we built a shed, he'd been pleased.
- How could he not be? It's a shed.
-  Do you think he's going to...
come out of the house again?
And kill us? Yes.
MAY: Sir Steve
really was incandescent,
so, Jeremy volunteered
to be Henry Kissinger.
And, despite this,
Sir Steve's mood did brighten.
CLARKSON: It doesn't look good.
But imagine, okay?
Summer's evenings sitting out here,
the sun streaming over there,
the fallen over digger.
Sorry about that.
Yes, he... There was an accident there.
But look at the greenhouse,
though, Sir Steve.
The greenhouse looks good.
The greenhouse is lovely,
the Poles built that and it works.
This, I think you'll find
is the pièce de résistance.
This... you see the water feature?
Now, what I've done is I've kind of
turbocharged the pump a bit.
All right, okay.
- Can you stand back a little bit?
- Because...
No, no, no, it's... you know like,
you've got a dribble, normally?
Of water? It'll now...
Be... It'll be, you know...
I-It's turbocharged.
You'll think of rowing. I think it now...
speaks of the man.
I've been trying for the last
eight years to not think about rowing.
Ready, Sir Steve?
There we go.
Oh, god.
[glass shatters]
I'm sorry about what
it's done to the greenhouse.
Yeah, that's unfortunate.
So, there you are...
Sir Steve Redgrave,
Lady Ann, children,
this is your new garden.
A rockery as well.
- Yeah, I blew that up.
- That's a long story.